<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A friendly debate between Dr. Kingsman, a dissatisfied clergy-man, and Gratianus Trimmer, a neighbour minister concerning the late thanksgiving-day, the Prince's desent [sic] into England, the nobility and gentries joining with him, the acts of the honourable convention, the nature of our English government, the secret league with France, the oaths of allegiance and supremacy, &amp;c. : with some considerations on Bishop Sanderson and Dr. Falkner about monarchy, oaths, &amp;c. ... / by a minister of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Kingsman, Dr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18348</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12869626</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12869626</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94791</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40488)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94791)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 380:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A friendly debate between Dr. Kingsman, a dissatisfied clergy-man, and Gratianus Trimmer, a neighbour minister concerning the late thanksgiving-day, the Prince's desent [sic] into England, the nobility and gentries joining with him, the acts of the honourable convention, the nature of our English government, the secret league with France, the oaths of allegiance and supremacy, &amp;c. : with some considerations on Bishop Sanderson and Dr. Falkner about monarchy, oaths, &amp;c. ... / by a minister of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Kingsman, Dr.</author>
                  <author>Minister of the Church of England.</author>
                  <author>Trimmer, Gratianus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 78, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. 78.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: [2] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sanderson, Robert, 1587-1663.</term>
               <term>Falkner, William, d. 1682.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1714</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94791:1"/>
            <head>The Publiſher to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THeſe Papers were ſent me by a very Worthy Divine of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Upon the peruſal of which I found (with ſubmiſſion to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Judgments) the late and preſent Proceedings ſo well vindicated, and all Scruples ariſing from the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Affairs, ſo well anſwered, that I judg it would be very injurious to the Publick (tho the Author, through his great Modeſty, hath mean thoughts of his own Performances) if I ſhould have returned them to be buried in a Desk.</p>
            <p>I know indeed, ſeveral Treatiſes have been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed of late, with great Judgment and Satisfaction on ſeveral Points here handled, (particularly about the Old and New Oaths) but none as I know of have ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together all the Parts of the great Revolutions in <hi>England,</hi> and repreſented them in their true Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, as is performed in this <hi>Friendly Debate,</hi> to the great ſatisfaction of all that are truly ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and even to the Conviction of ſuch among us, who earneſtly invited the <hi>Deliverer</hi> (our preſent King <hi>William</hi>) but now very ungratefully reject that <hi>Deliverance,</hi> of which God hath made him a Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Inſtrument.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94791:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>Friendly Debate</hi> BETWEEN Dr. <hi>Kingſman,</hi> a Diſſatisfied Clergy-man, AND <hi>Gratianus Trimmer,</hi> a Neighbour Miniſter, CONCERNING The late Thankſgiving-Day; the Prince's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent into <hi>England;</hi> the Nobility and Gentries joining with him; the Acts of the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Convention; the Nature of our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Government; the Secret League with <hi>France;</hi> the Oaths of Allegiance and Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With ſome Conſiderations on Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Falkner,</hi> about Monarchy, Oaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written for the Satisfaction of ſome of the Clergy, and others that yet labour under Scruples.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Miniſter of the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>Ionathan Robinſon,</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb facs="tcp:94791:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94791:2"/>
            <head>A FRIENDLY DEBATE BETWEEN Dr. <hi>KING'S-MAN</hi> AND <hi>GRATIANUS TRIMMER,</hi> About the THANKS GIVING-DAY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King's-Man.</speaker>
               <p>GOod Morrow to you Sir, I am come to ſee you this Monday Morning, to Recreate my ſelf with you, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to find you to Day at leiſure to diſcourſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Trimmer.</speaker>
               <p>Sir I am glad to ſee you here, a Sign that the Times are come about, or elſe I ſhould not have thought of ſuch a Favour from you. And I am glad to hear you uſe the Word Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create, a good ſign that you took Pains Yeſterday, that you deſire Recreation to Day. I pray Sir, be pleaſed to take a Chair. I was juſt now thinking what Text to preach upon next Thurſday, the <hi>Thankſgiving-Day.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>Had you any Legal Notice of it, or Orders from the Biſhop?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>No Sir, but I hear there is a Book come to Mr.—of— and tho they care not for the Service, I look'd for one from the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritor, for the ſake of the Shilling.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>And did you give notice of it in the Church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>And what Text have you thought on?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I have thought of thoſe Words, <hi>Judges</hi> 5.9. <hi>My Heart is toward the Governours of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>that offered themſelves willingly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94791:3"/>the People: Bleſs ye the Lord.</hi> But I may pitch upon another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>Is not that in the ſame Chapter, with that Rebellious Text? <hi>Curſe ye Meroz.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, it is. But I thought there had been never a Rebellious Text in Scripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>No, And therefore it will be hard for you to find one for a Thankſgiving, on this Occaſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſo? Do you think Rebellion to be the occaſion of this Thankſgiving? But if there were ſuch a bad Text in the Word of God, I would find a better for this Occaſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>I thought what the <hi>Whiggs</hi> and <hi>Trimmers</hi> would at laſt bring us to.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>So you ſee indeed, that the <hi>Trimmers</hi> (the fineſt Nick-name that was ever given to honeſt Men, that were for the ſettlement of Affairs on the trueſt bottom) have brought the Boat to a ſight of Land, and I wiſh it well at Home in the Haven of Reſt and Peace. But do you know whither you were going, in the <hi>Royal James,</hi> hanging out the Flags of Loyalty; and by an Arbitrary Power, againſt all Law, preſſing all the Veſſels in the River to carry the Pope and Cardinals, to viſit <hi>England,</hi> with all their Stuff, and Merchandize, and to command all that would not go, paſſively to lower, and ſtrike Flag to you, or elſe to be ſunk?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But you do not blame us for our Loyalty, do ye? The Church of <hi>England,</hi> and her Friends, have been ever Loyal: And it is her Honour, which ſhe hath never proſtituted yet; whatever other Reformed Churches have done, that Honour of Loyalty is peculiar to our Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>No, I do not blame you for Loyalty, in the trueſt Notion of it, which the <hi>Trimmer</hi> underſtands better than any of you. His No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it is, that Loyalty is Duty and Obedience according to Law. And as for the Glory of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is called, and ſaid to be peculiar to her, I do think her Siſters beyond-Sea are as honeſt as ſhe; and whatever your Mother is, ſome of you her Sons have got no Honour by making Court to the Mother of Harlots. And they who can diſparage their Aunts abroad, or diſown them as no Siſter-Churches, becauſe they have not Lords for their Husbands, and wear not the ſame Dreſſes, do not conſult the Honour of their own Mother. And I doubt they will have but few Friends left 'em, who abandon them as no Friends to the Church, who have appeared
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94791:3"/>in this Cauſe. But becauſe you are ſo civil as to give me a Viſit, I will not diſpleaſe you, by a reherſal of the famous Actions of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and Heats, or ingenious Diſcourſes of Government, produced by your Friends. As you were very near to be deſtroyed with us by your over officiouſneſs, ſo I am abraid your ill tempered Loyalty will prove pernicious to ſome, and that you will yet endanger all, by that kind of Loyalty which ſome have called a principal Article of Religion. Loyalty is one of the prime Duties of the Fifth Commandment, and it relates to an object Duty placed, and to a Rule plainly determined. I will be Loyal to a Popiſh King, but if I may not have the King, but I muſt be in danger of being corrupted by Popery, or ſuffering to extremity by it; I think I have cauſe to adore the Providence which hath delivered me from both, without Blood, and Deſtruction upon Deſtruction. If the King had kept his Religion to Himſelf, tho he made the worſt choice, and not gone about to impoſe it, and ſet it up upon the Ruine of the Government, He might have governed the Kingdom in Peace and Honour. But it being out of his own Power, ſince he ſubjected himſelf to the Conduct of the moſt Peſtilent Society in the World, to have his Faith to Himſelf, without forcing it upon his unwilling Subjects, you can never preſerve the Virgin Virtue of Loyalty from being guilty of commiting Folly in <hi>England.</hi> And ſo being Loyal to the King, as you call it, you are Diſloyal to Chriſt the Supream Head of the Church, and treacherous to the Souls of many that are liable to Temptation, to yield to its Charms, or be expoſed to its Furies. You muſt chooſe either Holy-Water, or Blood. Had he been driven away by the Flaming Sword of Rebellious Subjects, you might have ſome pretence for your Murmurings, but not daring to truſt his own great Force, nor the Men of his own Religion, and having no Confidence in God, whoſe tremendous Providence hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed him away: I think you have no cauſe to wiſh for him again; but to think that well done, which God hath done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But can you think the Nation innocent in this matter? And if our Deliverance from ſome Miſchiefs be conſiderable, yet if the People have ſinned, we have ſmall cauſe to be thankful. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I have no Legal Command from my Ordinary, and that <hi>Aſh-Wedneſday</hi> is the Day before; I will keep that, and hope no notice will be taken for my not obſerving the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>And why not both? I am ſure you have not been ſo nice about other Thankſgivings.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:94791:4"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>I have no Book.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Our Prayers for the Queen and Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> were commonly called Modeſt Prayers.</note>Then you want a Book of Prayers modeſtly penn'd. Will you do nothing from your Heart, no more than you will do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Order by the Apparitor on your own Head? But will you read the Litany, and Denunciations, <hi>ſicut olim,</hi> as you are commanded to do on <hi>Aſh-Wedneſday;</hi> or will you omit them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>I will do as the Law requires, and according to my Declaration of Aſſent to all and every thing contained in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Then you will ſtill pray for the King, tho he deſerted the Kingdom, not as much as leaving a Commiſſion for Adminiſtrators in his Abſence; then you will pray that he may be kept and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved <hi>in the true worſhipping of God,</hi> which he hath not done ſince he became a Papiſt; then you will pray for the <hi>Queen</hi> and <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> ſtill, right or wrong; and that God would <hi>give the King the victory over all his Enemies.</hi> What without fighting? And who are they? Are they reputed his Enemies, or his Friends who ſign'd the Aſſociation at <hi>Guild-Hall?</hi> and do you pray, he may be in a condition to fight againſt them, and overcome them too? And who will you mean when you denounce him Curſed who removeth his Neighbours Landmark? The King who turn'd out the Preſident, and Fellows of <hi>Magdalen-Colledg</hi> (which is a little more, than gaining a little Ground by removing the Land-marks:) or the Convention, who labour to find out the ancient Bounds, and Foundations remov'd by Arbitrary Goverment? for my part, I deal truly with you, I cannot pray every Petition, contained in the Book of Common-Prayer, notwithſtanding Aſſent declared, for tho there be no Alterations made in the Book, there is an Alteration made in Things and Perſons that I look upon my ſelf, as ſo far diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from the Obligation of the Act, except I ſhould offer that to God, which I believe he will not accept.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>Then you will preſume to make publick Prayers of your own, without Authority?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">When this was written, I had no Book, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than looſe a Shilling for a Book not worth Two Pence, after the Rate of Paper and Print, ſo baſely Printed that it would even blind a pair of Specticles to read it; I had one ſent me the Evening before, in which there was no Order for a Sermon, nor Homily againſt Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. And therefore they who preached not that Day may plead their Excuſe, for none was required.</note>Why not pray without a Book, as well as preach without One? on ſuch an Occaſion as this, eſpecially. If Superiors neglect their Duty, I know no reaſon why I ſhould neglect mine. The Scripture is as full of matter for Prayer and Praiſe, as for Preaching. And altho God hath by his Providence, as much as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94791:4"/>blotted out ſeveral parts of the Common-Prayer, and tranſported the King, yet that Command, and Act of his Will continues ſtill in force, <hi>Let Prayers, and Supplications, and giving of Thanks be made for all men, for Kings, and ſuch as are in Authority.</hi> There are ſome ſtill in Authority, and therefore I am obliged to pray for them, and to give Thanks. And tho I cannot make Verſicles, for a Dialogue between the Miniſter and Clerk, there are Pſalms and Chapters as proper for this ſervice, as for other, and I hope more proper than thoſe for the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and the Queen's being with Child, and I might name more than thoſe. And I hope to find matter enough for a large Thankſgiving.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But where will you find Precedents in Scripture for the Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of Subjects againſt their Lawful Prince and Soveraign? or for a Son and Nephew to invade the Kingdom of his Father and Uncle? or for a Convention of Subjects to depoſe their natural Lord and King?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I might ask you as many Queſtions on the other ſide: But not to tire my ſelf with talk to Day, I will come home to the Preſent Caſe, and lay all theſe things together.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">The Caſe openedt</note>1. The King being a Zealous Papiſt, (wiſhing all his Subjects were of his Religion, in the Declaration of Indulgence) and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by the Jeſuits, it is impoſſible for him to keep his Word, or Declarations made to his Proteſtant Subjects, any further than ſhall ſerve their Deſigns, and Intereſts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How the King kept his Promiſes to govern by Law, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade no Mans Property, to maintain the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ask the Judges, enquire at <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the late Chancellor, and Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſioners.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Popery was diſſeminated all over the Land, Maſs-Houſes publick, Papiſts put in Offices, Schools opened, and taught by Jeſuits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> contrary to Law.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The King declared Himſelf abſolute, having an inherent power in Himſelf to diſpence with Statutes. Another Argument, that there was no hold to be taken of his Word or Promiſes. For if he do not keep the Statutes made by his Royal Aſſent and his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, how can we expect firmneſs in verbal Promiſes and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations? And if his Power be Arbitrary, and abſolute, he may change and recede from his Word, as often as he doth change his Mind, and Councils.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:94791:5"/>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">King <hi>James II.</hi> chang'd the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</note>5. He changed the form of Government, and Conſtitution from an Engliſh Monarchy, and Independent; from an imperial Crown, to a ſubjection to the Pope, and See of <hi>Rome.</hi> And whether He be any longer King of <hi>England,</hi> than he is Supreme in his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and that in Oppoſition to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> by Name, I dare refer it to your ſelf. He hath loſt his legal claim to the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> by Subjection to the Roman Pontiff.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But tho he has, yet the Order and Authority of Kings being of the Law of Nature, He is Sovereign ſtill, tho he hath degraded Himſelf from the dignity and Supremacy of the King of <hi>England,</hi> by the Law of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Sir You are miſtaken in that Point; for you cannot ſay that the Superiority of the Pope over Kings, is of the Law of Nature; if not, then that King that is Superior above all in his Dominions by the Law of Nature, and yet doth ſubject himſelf to the Pope, doth give up his Natural Right to one that hath no Natural Right, and doth thereby violate, and change the Conſtitution of Nature, and therefore hath loſt His Claim to a Soveraignty by Nature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But the Scripture doth eſtabliſh the Order and Superiority of Kings, and therefore he holds his Crown and Scepter, by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Patent, and Divine Right. <hi>Can.</hi> 1640.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I ask you again, Doctor, Is the Supremacy of the Pope o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Kings by Divine Right? if over Kings by Divine Right, then much more over you and me: (if you grant it, ſo will not I) But he hath no Divine right to a Supremacy over Kings, and yet the King hath Submitted to it; therefore hath he not loſt and forfeited his Pretence to Soveraignty by Scripture, and Divine Right? and by conſequence, hath he any Right to Soveraign Dominion? I put it to you. Beſide, the Scripture doth conſtitute a perpetual form of Government.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But your ſuppoſed Wrong, is a wrong to Himſelf. And our Relation of Subjects to him, is unalterable, and perpetual.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>You are out again, by your favour, as I conceive with reſpect to your dignity. For the Wrong is a Publick, and General Wrong to all his Proteſtants Subjects, and not a private Injury to Himſelf onely.<note place="margin">The Relation of Subjects to the King.</note> Our relation as Subjects, is to a King, and we are Subjects no longer than he is King, as we are no longer Children, than we have Parents: if he ceaſe to be a King by Subjection to the Pope, I am diſcharged from being a Subject; for I am a Subject to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94791:5"/>King, and not to him who is no King, or hath made Himſelf none. My relation to the King is to a Royal Perſon, veſted with Royal Authority, and the Law of the Land is the Meaſure and Bond of that Relation. If the Perſon to whom I am related, have diſrobed Himſelf of his Royalty, tho the Natural Perſon be in Being, yet the King is gone; as Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> ſaid, the Lord Chancellor is gone, when his Perſon was there preſent, but out of his Office.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But how then came the Peers and People of <hi>England</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him at his Coronation, and in Parliament, if his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and Submiſſion to the Pope made him none?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I did not at firſt intend to ſpeak of theſe tender points, but you began it, and I hope you will not make an ill uſe of it. I give you my anſwer clearly.
<list>
                     <item>1. The Peers, and People own'd him as King at his Coronation, for then he ſwore, or was thought to ſwear to govern by Laws.</item>
                     <item>2. In Parliament, (if that may be called a Parliament, who had a great Number, that were not E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by the Commons, but returned by Arbitrary Sheriffs and Mayors) he appear'd in his Legal Capacity acting according to Law.</item>
                     <item>3. The Peers and People ſuffered quietly and dutifully, till their Conſciences could bear no more, or their Heads, Families and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity were near Deſtruction. There was all Dutifulneſs and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, Tribute and Cuſtoms paid him by all Ranks and Degrees of Men, as long as there was any Hopes.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. As he altered the Government in his own perſonal Dignity, ſo he manifeſtly deſtroy'd the other part of the Conſtitution, the Right and Liberty of the People in free Elections, and frequent Parliaments; and ſo no part of the Government was ſafe.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And to entail our Miſeries, there was an Infant ſet up for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heriter of the Crown, of whoſe Natural Deſcent no legal Proof was made, or can be, as is rationally preſum'd. And by the way the King could not be ſafe, but during the pleaſure of the Jeſuits, who having an Infant King, and who could raiſe a Succeſſion, as faſt as one died, could domineer the more, and ſend the King to the other World.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <note place="margin">The Nation paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive as long as there was any hope of Redreſs.</note>8. There was no hope left of Redreſs of preſent Grievances, or prevention of utter ruine to the Proteſtant Intereſt of the Kingdom. And conſider, that theſe things were not perſonal Infirmities and Defects, or Male-Adminiſtrations, or private Injuries and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; But the greateſt Violation of Truſt, and Breach of the Conſtitution, that was ever avowedly made, growing hard upon a down-right overthrow, and utter Ruine.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:94791:6"/>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> There was a Deſtructive Conjunction of Intereſt and Deſign with a Foraign Tyrant to bring us and our deareſt Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into like Condition with <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Savoy.</hi> Were not the <hi>French</hi> Aſſiſtances expected, to turn beautiful <hi>England</hi> to an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celdama?</hi> What made the Prieſt in the Lady <hi>Cary's</hi> Houſe, conclude the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet to be their Friends the <hi>French,</hi> for whoſe Entertainment great Proviſions were made, and to go to the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to Sing <hi>Te Deum?</hi> Sir, We have as great Cauſe to keep every day of <hi>November</hi> as a Thankſgiving, as we have to keep the 5th, now challenging our Thankſgiving to all Generations, for our Deliverance from the Powder Plot, and League with <hi>France,</hi> by the moſt Happy, Seaſonable and Succeſsful Arrival of his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> now our Elected King. Whom God long Preſerve, With his Royal Conſort, now our Gracious Queen.</p>
               <p>And now, Sir, Be pleas'd to ſpeak, what would you have us do?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>The Chriſtian Courſe is well known; Petitions, Prayers, Patience, Tears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>As for Petitions, you know the King ſent the Biſhops to the Tower for an Anſwer, and thence brought them to the Bar. A warning to Petitioners! Prayers were uſed, by ſuch as you know, rather to harden than ſoften the King's Heart. Was he not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to God, ſtill as his choſen Servant? Was he not pray'd for, as if he had worſhipped God in the beſt and only way? and ſeveral other Prayers little better. As for Patience, it was exerciſed to the laſt Day of Safety. And as for Tears, we durſt not ſhed them for the King, nor for our ſelves under him, for by <hi>Innuendo's</hi> they had been Seditious. What! keep an Anniverſary of Joy for his coming to the Throne, and weep too? We had cauſe, more than we knew, of a long time to weep and howl too, for the Miſeries that were coming upon us. Had not God moſt ſeaſonably and powerfully turn'd the Stream of the Proceedings of our Adverſarics, all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that would not bow the Knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> had been a <hi>Bochim,</hi> a Vale of Tears. How uſeful and divine ſoever this Perſuaſion to Prayers and Tears may be, yet when I conſider for whoſe Service theſe Exhortations, were ſo openly made, even for theirs (tho not ſo intended) who have the ſharpeſt Bryars and Thorns to whip Slaves into Tears, and then put an end to their Praying, by cutting their Throats, much of that Preaching might have been ſpared.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94791:6"/>There are many Evangelical Doctrines neceſſary to Salvation rarely touch't upon by ſuch Preachers. I do much wiſh there were Streams of penitent Tears ruuning from our Eyes, and more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant Prayers of the Righteous ſent up to Heaven. But notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great Scarcity of both, I think it a great Duty to give thanks to God, for delivering us from the Hands of our Enemies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>You do not know but the King's Heart might be changed. He did a great deal in a little time for the Satisfaction of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in reſtoring Charters, and declaring he would Call a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and offered Pardons to his Enemies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>We know theſe Acts of Grace, and when they were made publick. Of theſe ſee the Sence of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in his Declaration. What if the Counſellors and Tools adviſed theſe Acts, to Caſt us into a ſleep, and to gain time for <hi>French</hi> Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations? You may ſee what the Nation did, and what Methods of Proceedings were uſed.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">What Methods were uſed for our Preſervation.</note>1. Many of our Peers and Gentlemen of Honour and Intereſt, firſt repreſented the State of the Kingdom to the Heirs Expectant of the Crown, and therein declared, That their Higneſſes, if no Prince be born to the King, have an unqueſtionable Right to defend the Legal Monarchy, <hi>Rege etiam renitente.</hi> That the People of <hi>England</hi> have an Unqueſtionable Right to ſeek Aſſiſtance from their Royal Highneſſes.<note place="margin">Our Caſe ſtated on the Nations part.</note> That the Ancient Kings of <hi>England</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the Peoples Right to ſave their Free Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See the <hi>Memorial. p.</hi> 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Prince and Princeſs have Right to defend,<note place="margin">Note this.</note> and the People of <hi>England</hi> a Right to ſeek that Defence, wherein doth the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of both, or of either appear? eſpecially conſidering the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> being not an undoubted Heir.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Our Caſe ſtated on the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s part.</note>2. The Prince and Princeſs timely dealt with the King, in a moſt dutiful manner, propoſing Expedients to compoſe and ſettle the Nation; as appears by Penſioner <hi>Fagel's</hi> Letter, and Vindication. But the Contrivers of our Ruine, both in Soul and Body, proceeding to obſtruct all healing Methods; His High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs put forth his pious and juſt Declaration of his Reaſons and Intentions to come over into <hi>England.</hi> The Reflections upon it are very wordy, and weak. See the Declaration.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had no Intereſt by proximity of Blood to ſeek the Preſervation of the Church and Kingdom, Why might not he come over to us, as righteouſly to deliver us, as Our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94791:7"/>former Kings, and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> have aſſiſted forreign Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant States, and Sufferers, by Money and Arms?</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Miſeries of the Proteſtants in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the Dangers which threatned all Proteſtant Kingdoms and Sates, by the Power and Blood-thirſtineſs of <hi>France,</hi> and the Popiſh Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates; awakened Proteſtant Kings and Princes to prevent the Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of their Countries and Religion, to enter into a League, and to begin with <hi>England,</hi> to reſcue it from its growing Perils, and to ſettle the State of it, as knowing what an Influence its Preſervation or Deſtruction would have upon Countries of the ſame Profeſſion. And his Highneſs the Prince being ſo deeply en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in that League, he muſt, as a Chriſtian, prefer the Glory of Chriſt, before all Obligations of Relation as a Son and a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew. Yet ſtill performing all the Duties of that Relation, in which he hath not been wanting, as far as is conſiſtent with the Common Cauſe and Intereſt. And reſpect to the Common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Intereſt and Engagement, prevail'd with his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Denmark</hi> to go over to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> as he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth in his Letter to the King.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Prince in his Declaration invited All Degrees and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Men in the Kingdom to come in and joyn with him, to promote his Ends, in getting a Free Parliament, to which he refers Himſelf, and the Settlement of Church and State. Should the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Gentry look on, and ſee him ready to Fight in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and give him no Aſſiſtance?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, certainly! for they ought not to aſſiſt an Invader a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their King.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Caſe ſtated reſteth upon this as one chief Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</note>If they have right to relate their Grievances and Preſſures, and to call him to their Reſcue, there being <hi>no other way left for them;</hi> and if he have Right and Intereſt in <hi>England,</hi> which he cannot give up for loſt; and if that which he deſires, is neither Crown, nor Conquest, but the Preſervation of the Government, in a lawful Parliamentary-way, then the Invaſion is not the Invaſion of an Enemy, but the coming in of a Saviour to deliver us. That the People of <hi>England</hi> have right to defend their Government, they prove in the <hi>Memorial,</hi> quoted before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But do not you know that Private Perſons are not fit Judges, whether their Preſent Caſe be ſuch, in which they may lawfully reſiſt or no?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:94791:7"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I remember ſomething to that purpoſe in Dr. <hi>Falkner,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chriſtian Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> Book 2. p. 365. p. 373.</note> and he quotes the more Corrected Judgment of <hi>Grotius</hi> (differing from what he had written in his younger Time) upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. But, Are the wiſeſt Noblemen, Gentry and Lawyers of the Land unfit to Judg of this Caſe? Doth their incapacity to judge riſe from the Privacy of their Condition? or what elſe? A private Man well ſtudied in the Laws and Conſtitution, is as able to judge when that is Uiolated, as more Publick Perſons, and a good Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer in his Study knows the Law as well as many a Judg upon the Bench. Beſides I diſtinguiſh between a particular private Man,<note place="margin">The Nobles and Gentry who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in this Action, not meer private Men.</note> or more ſuſtaining private Injuries or Oppreſſions, or ſome leſſer Bodies and Corporations, and the Community of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. They who have appeared for the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> are by far the Majority of the whole Kingdom, and men of as great Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, as any of thoſe who drove them to this Courſe. This Reſiſtance was not in a private Cauſe but the Eſſentials of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and Concern of the Kingdom. And therefore, what the Doctor ſaith, and quoteth out of <hi>Grotius,</hi> is nothing to our Caſe.</p>
               <p>And, for a fuller underſtanding of our Caſe, I pray, Sir, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what the King did.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Our Caſe opened on the Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> part.</note>The Prince, and Majority of the Kingdom declare for a Free Parliament, for the Proteſtant Religion, and for the Laws, and Government by Law. Can any King that is a King by Law, ſworn, and obliged by Promiſes to govern by Law, refuſe to grant what the Kingdom deſires?</p>
               <p>But He on the Contrary,
<list>
                     <item>1. Prepares a Royal Navy, increaſeth his ſtanding Army, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in many thouſands of Popiſh Iriſh, and of Scots, tho not all Papiſts, yet as he thought for his purpoſe.</item>
                     <item>2. Tho he declared he would ſummon a free Parliament, yet he ſent out but few Writs, which came to nothing.</item>
                     <item>3. He prepares to defend his Cauſe, and to oppoſe the Prince and Kingdom by the Sword: Whereas if he had pleaſed in conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient time to call a free Parliament, he had ſatisfied his Subjects.</item>
                     <item>4. When the Prince advanced, the King went out in Perſon to his Army, declaring an intention to fight.</item>
                     <item>5. But when the Armies were not far aſunder, and an Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment expected by the Prince, Behold! the Soveraign Power of the Lord of Hoſts upon the Spirit of the King, He deſerted his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94791:8"/>upon which he laid the whole of his Cauſe; And ſo far he quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Cauſe, which was to be maintained by Force, and not by a Legal Parliament.</item>
                     <item>6. And laſtly, as you very well know, he gave up his Army and Navy to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and went off, without Force or Threatning; for what Reaſons, or upon whoſe Advice, is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together Unknown.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the whole of what I have very briefly exerciſed your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience with, I conclude, Our <hi>Caſe is Extraordinary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Our Caſe in all Circumſtances extraordinary.</note>It is Extraordinary;
<list>
                     <item>1. That our King ſhould be a Papiſt, and ſubject to the Abhorred Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. That he ſhould overthrow the Foundations, tho not pull down all the Superſtructions of the Government, and begin with his own Soveraign Dignity, own a Superior, the Pope, to whom he ſent an Ambaſſadour, and from whom he entertained a Nuncio.</item>
                     <item>3. That he ſhould go about to force, and pack a Parliament, and therein deſtroy the Liberties of the Subject, which are as legal as his Prerogatives.</item>
                     <item>4. That when a Parliament is deſired, He choſe rather to put his Cauſe upon the Swords Point, and really into the Hands and upon the Determination of God, who is the Lord of Hoſts, tho he did not refer it to the Judgment of God formally, and in words, than into a legal peaceable way.</item>
                     <item>5. And having deſerted his Army without Battel, I deſire your Information of me whether it was not a giving up of his Cauſe?</item>
                     <item>6. It was altogether extraordinary too, that Subjects might not have encouragement to Petition for their juſt Rights, when they ſaw Ruine drawing on, by the encreaſe of Popery, and Combinations of Papiſts to root out the Proteſtant Religion, according to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of their Church. And being debarred of any Legal Means, the moſt Eminent of the Kingdom (not the <hi>Plebs,</hi> and <hi>Vulgus,</hi> the private Men, that are judged unfit to judg of their Rights and Dangers) call for Aſſiſtance from the Heirs Expectant; that the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Prince ſhould enter the Kingdom with an Army, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the Kingdom were ready to aſſiſt according to their Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; that he ſhould march ſo many Miles without a Skirmiſh; and inſtead of finding a Royal Army in a poſture to fight, he found it diſcharg'd from fighting, by the King Himſelf: And in fine, found an open and uninterrupted Paſſage to Royal Palaces, and the whole
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94791:8"/>Force of the King delivered up to him. If this be not rare and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary,<note place="margin">By a Letter from the King to him.</note> never was the Finger of God ſeen in any wonderful Work and Turn. This is the mighty Work of God! whom won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful in working! And extraordinary Providences, being either in Mercy, or in Judgment; I ſee a great deal of Mercy, a Mercy as great and extraordinary, as the appearance of the Hand that gave it to us. And I make no queſtion, but the Night that was coming upon us, would have been as diſmal and dreadful, as the Day of our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is glorious and memorable.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>I own the Providence is extraordinary, and the Action with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out example. But ſtill how can you publickly rejoice, at the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of a Rebellion againſt our Soveraign? Is it not againſt eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed Laws? and againſt our Oaths?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I will be as brief with you as may be.
<list>
                     <item>1. Can ſinful Men do any thing without Sin? And is it not one of the Perfections of God to carry on his own Purpoſes, by thoſe very Actions of Men that are ſinful, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.20. and many Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hereof might be given.</item>
                     <item>2. There were many and great Sins committed, before the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was provoked to this extraordinary Courſe; Arbitrary Power is ſubverſive of the Conſtitution and Laws of this Kingdom, and the Advancement of Popery the introducing of all manner of Sins and Miſeries.</item>
                     <item>
                        <note place="margin">No ordinary Rules for extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Caſes.</note>3. In extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Caſes, we are carried beyond ordinary Rules. As there is no written Law, to warrant the Subjects taking up Arms againſt the King, but forbidding them; ſo there is no Law of God, or Man, that warrants the King's turning his Power and Sword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Subjects. The one is as unlawful as the other. There is not an Oath given by the Subjects to the King, but the King is in Conſcience bound to anſwer by his goodneſs to them.</item>
                     <item>4. Our Conſtitution and Laws, do ſuppoſe an intire Union of Affection, Intereſt, yea and Religion too, between the King and his People. And as expreſs Laws and formal Oaths do forbid Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects taking Arms, and other Acts of Diſobedience, ſo the very Being, and Relation of a King, and Rules of Government, bind him as faſt, not to oppreſs them, or invade their Rights. They have Rights, and are a People as free from Tyranny, as any people in the World.</item>
                     <item>5. Then ſtricteſt Obligations in Religion and Conſcience mutual between King and People, muſt always ſuppoſe God's Soveraign
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94791:9"/>Right to diſpoſe of Kingdoms, to put down one and ſet up another. And it is ſuitable, to think that when God doth appear by great providences, great Changes follow. Hitherto we ſee extraordinary Mercies! And I beſeech you, ſhew me wherein have the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> ſinned againſt the Perſon, Crown, or Dignity of the King, to neceſſitate him, to prepare Armies againſt them, who were conſtrained to take Arms, or be deſtroyed by Papiſts?</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But tho God doth act according to his abſolute Dominion, yet he acts according to his infinite Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, or Mercy; and tho His infinite Majeſty doth whatſoever pleaſeth him, yet we muſt walk according to Rules, and keep our Places. Now the King of <hi>England</hi> being a Soveraign Prince, Supreme over All Perſons, and we being bound by ſo many Oaths to maintain his Crown and Dignity, and not to take Arms againſt his Perſon, or thoſe who are Comiſſioned by him, on any Pretence whatſoever, this Action muſt needs be unlawful in it ſelf, and not the leſs ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, becauſe ſucceſsful.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I will take your Reaſons in Order. And becauſe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not carry Books in Memory, and ſhall have recourſe to ſome few, I pray let us go to my Study, if you can ſtay there ſo long without a Fire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>Come let's then, I can endure the Cold as well as your ſelf.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Abſolute Kings no Ordinance of God.</note>1. Then, I cannot believe that God or Nature ever gave an abſolute Power to Kings. An Abſolute King, is ſo called, becauſe he is, <hi>non Legibus ſolutus,</hi> not bound by Laws. One that gives Laws to Others, but is above all Laws, and not tied to any Himſelf. When God did foreſee that his People <hi>Iſrael</hi> would in time grow weary of the Theocracy, God's Government over them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be governed like other Nations, yet that King that ſhould govern them was to be bound to obſerve the Law, in the Statute-Book of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. from the 15th to the 20th Verſe. No one Man ſince the Fall was Wiſe, or Righteous, or Powerful enough, to have the abſolute and Arbitrary Rule of any people. And I ſuppoſe Tyranny is not an Ordinance of God, but a Corruption of Government.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But conſider what the learned, judicious and Excellent Writer of our Church,<note place="margin">Bp. <hi>Saunderſon</hi> conſidered.</note> Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon</hi> ſaith of this. <hi>Preface be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Arch-Biſhop</hi> Uſher's <hi>Treatiſe of Power communicated by God to the Prince.</hi> Sect. 12.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94791:9"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I have conſidered it, and have wondred, to read theſe words. <hi>True it is that for more eaſe of Governours, and better ſatisfaction of the People, in ſecuring their Properties, preſerving Peace among them, and doing Juſtice, the abſolute and unlimited Soveraignty which Princes have by the Ordinance of God, hath at all Times, and in all Nations been diverſly limitted and bounded in the ordinary Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe thereof, by ſuch Laws and Cuſtoms as the Supreme Governours themſelves have conſented unto and allowed, As</hi> with us <hi>in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>Now, Doctor, with all due reſpect to you, and that great Writer, I offer you theſe Reflections.
<list>
                  <item>1. He affirms that the <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and unlimited</hi> Soveraignty which Princes have by the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if they have an unlimited Soveraignty (which I acknowledge they muſt needs have, if it be abſolute) by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God, how dare they conſent to limit it, which is to change the Ordinance of God?</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Soveraignty of the King of <hi>England</hi> limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note>2. <hi>As in England,</hi> &amp;c. then I ſay, the Soveraignty of the King of <hi>England</hi> is bounded by Laws and Cuſtoms, and therefore not abſolute and unlimited.</item>
                  <item>3. Tho their Soveraignty be limited by their own Conſent, it is limited af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Conſent is given.</item>
                  <item>4. It is limited by their own Conſent, as all other Statute-Laws are made by their Conſent, and what they conſent to, is paſt by the Conſent of the Lords and Commons in Parliament firſt.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Orlando Bridgman,</hi> afterwards Lord Keeper, in his charge to the Grand-Jury of <hi>Middleſex</hi> at the Trial of the Regicides, took pains to declare our Government, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. He opens the Power of our Kings, from the Titles that are given them in Law-Books, and moſt upon the Title Imperial Crown, ſubject to God, and to no other Power. 
<q>What is an Imperial Crown? it is that, which as to the Coercive part, is ſubject to no Man under God, humane Tribunal, or Judicature whatſoever, <bibl>
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 11, 12.</bibl> God forbid I ſhould intend any Abſolute Government by this! And <bibl>
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 68.</bibl> Yet let me tell you, there is that excellent ☜ temperament in our Laws that, for all this, the King cannot rule but by his Laws, <bibl>
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 12.</bibl> Tho this is an abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, yet this is ſo far from infringing the Peoples Rights; that the People as to their Properties, Liberties, and Lives, have as great a Priviledge as the King. <bibl>
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 13.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But read further, and then you will ſee, that when he ſaith, <q>We have as great Liberties as any People have in Chriſtendom, in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94791:10"/>the World, he adds, But let us own them where they are due. We owe them to the Conceſſions of our Princes. Our Princes have granted them; and the King, now; He in them hath granted them likewiſe. Therefore the King is the Fountain of all the Liberties of the People, they are his Gracious Conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>That will not help you to infer, that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> are abſolute unlimited Soveraigns. There are no People in the world give greater honour to their Kings, than we of <hi>England,</hi> as the learned Sir <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> Privy Councellor to Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> and Embaſſador in <hi>France,</hi> when he wrote his Book <hi>De Repub. Anglorum, pag.</hi> 47. Their way of asking any thing in Parliament, tho they <hi>have right to the thing,</hi> is by way of Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and as Subjects; and do acknowledge all the good Acts to be the Gracious Acts of the King. But there are two ſorts of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions and Grants.
<list>
                     <item>1. Such as are Conceſſions of meer Grace, of ſuch Benefits, as the Commons have no right to Claim. And,</item>
                     <item>2. There are Conceſſions of Right, and ſignify no more, than the King doth Conſent to ſuch Bills, as are preſented by the Lords and Commons; and ſo all our Rights and Properties ſecured by Law, are Conceſſions.</item>
                  </list>
And all thoſe Conceſſions, as Grants and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that are more Acts of Grace than ſome others are, are for ſome publick Benefit, and redound to the King's Honour, Profit, or Service: And ſuch Conceſſions as theſe flow from Prerogative, which Prerogative, as all Legal Prerogatives are the King by Law. There are mutual Acts of Kindneſs between a good King and his Subjects. And the Commonwealth is happy when ſuch mutual demonſtrations of Love, Grace, and Duty paſs between them. But there are Conceſſions alſo made to the King by his Subjects in Parliament, which the King cannot have, but by the free Act of his Subjects, as Subſides and Taxes. And becauſe the Subjects grant them to the King, when they ſee it reaſonable; it is manifeſt, I conceive,<note place="margin">Will you ſuffer me hence to infer the Parliament is Supreme above the King, becauſe they make theſe Conceſſions?</note> that the People have Rights and Properties, and Liberties of their own. And many of theſe they come to by Purchaſe, and not Royal Donations; or by an Equivalence of ſome Bencht to the King. Read if you pleaſe, the learned Mr <hi>Lawſon,</hi> a good Civilian and Politician, as well as Divine, in his Anſwer to <hi>Hobs,</hi> c. 8. That learned and ingenious Gentleman Sir <hi>Dudley Diggs,</hi> ſpake to the Lords in a Conference, <hi>Anno</hi> 1628. <q>Be pleaſed to Know then, that it is an undoubted fundamental point of this ſo ancient Common
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94791:10"/>Law, (of which he ſaid <hi>Caput inter Nubila condit</hi>) of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that the Subject hath a true Property in his Goods and Poſſeſſions, which doth preſerve as ſacred that <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> that is the Nurſe of Induſtry, the Mother of Courage, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which there can be no Juſtice, of which <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> is the proper Object. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ephemeris Parliamentaris. pag.</hi> 95.</bibl>
                  </q> The Petition ſo much debated in that Parliament, was the Petition of Right. The King in his Anſwer to the whole Parliament, ſpake this Golden Sentence, <hi>And I aſſure you, my Maxim is, That the Peoples Liberties, ſtrengthen the King's Prerogative, and the Kings Prerogative is to defend the Peoples Liberties, pag.</hi> 204. Here's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>The People have Rights. But Government being before Property, <q>Property doth proceed from the Soveraign, who grants and determins it. For, as Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon</hi> aſſerts, <hi>Sect.</hi> 18. of the Preface, It is certain that as ſoon as <hi>Adam</hi> was created, God gave him to be an Univerſal Monarch. —and the Government alſo of all the inferior World, and of all the Men that after ſhould be born ſo long as he lived; ſo as whatſoever Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty any other perſon had or could have in any part of the World—they held it all of Him.—So after the Flood, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Property, or Share in the Government over any part of the World any of his Sons had, they had it by his ſole Allotment and Authority—without waiting for Election or Conſent, or entring into any Articles or Capitulations with the People that were to be governed by them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Is the Argument Good from <hi>Adam</hi> before the Fall, to the Government after the Fall? Is the Argument good from <hi>Adam</hi> the Common Father, or <hi>Noah,</hi> a Common Father to the State of the World, diſtinguiſhed and divided in the ſeveral Kingdoms, and Territories? Was <hi>Adam</hi>'s Monarchy Hereditary, to his eldeſt Son next in ſucceſſion? Did <hi>Cain</hi> ſucceed him in the Univerſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy? Or did <hi>Cain</hi> forfeit,<note place="margin">Did <hi>Adam</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot him the land of <hi>Nod?</hi>
                  </note> and ſo it deſcended to the next Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? To be brief with you:
<list>
                     <item>1. When Soveraign Princes are Nature Fathers, and give Portions to their Subject as to their Children; then let them be as Great in their Dominions, as <hi>Adam</hi> or as <hi>Noah</hi> was, provided they be kind and righteous, as they were.</item>
                     <item>2. The Law then in Being and Force was the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which eſtabliſhed Property, in the 8th Commandment.</item>
                  </list>
And Judgment, which is a Branch of Government or of Civil Power,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94791:11"/>doth ſuppoſe Property, as its Object, or Matter about which it is converſant. And there could be no actual Exerciſe of the judicial Port of Power and Government, but there was a Property to be judged of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How far the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is ſupreme.</note>But you cannot but ſay, that the King of <hi>England</hi> is the onely ſupreme Governour and Monarch; and if a Monarch, the Supremacy is in Him alone: for a Co-ordination of Power, and a mixt Monarchy, are abſurd contradictory Notions. As you may ſee in the Reverend Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sect</hi> 14.</note> Preface, <q>We are bound by our Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance to bear Faith and true Allegiance to the King and his Heirs and Succeſſors, and to aſſiſt and defend all Juriſdictions, <hi>&amp;c. Granted</hi> or belonging to him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
I pray read the Oaths. And then we are bound by the Oath of the 14. of <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, not to take Arms againſt the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon any pretence whatſoever, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſurely ſuch Actions, and Alterations as we know, and ſee of late, are utterly unlawful, and therefore I cannot joyn in the Thankſgiving for our Deliverance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, You put me upon a neceſſity of ſpeaking what other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I ſhould be as unwilling to diſcourſe of, as any other Man. But conceiving my ſelf obliged in Conſcience and Religion to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our wonderful Deliverance, I ſhall lay before you what I have learnt in theſe great matters.</p>
               <p>I know Sir. <hi>O. Bridgman</hi> did urge the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy upon the Regicides, and all that took Arms againſt the King, in the Trial of Mr. <hi>Scroop, pag.</hi> 67, 68. What is the <hi>Oath of Allegiance? is it not that you will defend the King, his Crown,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>againſt all Perſons whatſoever?</hi> It was not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pope,<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder favour, that word, <hi>Or otherwiſe,</hi> doth there ſignify, ſome other way or means, not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, by which the Pope might act againſt the King.</note> (as ſome would have it) but the word is, or <hi>Otherwiſe.</hi> They broke the Oath of Supremacy, which was, that the King was the ſupreme Governour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There is, ſaith he, a difference between ſome Crowns, and Imperial Crowns. An Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Crown is that which was not to be touched by any perſon: We do not ſpeak <hi>of the Abſolute Power of the King, pag.</hi> 68. The Reverend Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> builds his ſtrong Tower for defence of the King's Soveraignty upon the words of the Oath of Supremacy, That the King's Highneſs is the onely Supreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this Realm, Sect. 14. The quickeſt way to bring our diſcourſe to an iſſue, is to lay down, what I think very conſiderable in this matter.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:94791:11"/>
               <p n="1">1. We acknowledge the King, or Queen of <hi>England,</hi> to be the onely ſupreme Governour within his Dominions. But the Kings and Queens of <hi>England</hi> had no more Power given, or attributed to them, by theſe Oaths, or the Statutes enjoyning them, than they had before theſe Declarations. So Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> declared in her Injunction 1559.<note place="margin">Note this.</note> An Admonition to ſimple men deceived by the malitious, in the Collection of Doctor <hi>Sparrow, pag.</hi> 81. <q>The Queens Majeſty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> would that all her loving Subjects though underſtand, that nothing was, is, or ſhall be meant or intended by the ſame Oath to have any other Duty, Allegiance, or Bond required by the ſame Oath, than was acknowledged to be due to the moſt Noble Kings of famous Memory King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, or <hi>Edward</hi> the 6.—For certainly her Majeſty neither doth, nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will challenge any Authority, than what was challenedg, and lately uſed by the ſaid Noble Kings of famous Memory, King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, or <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, which is and was of ancient time due to the Imperial Crown of this Realm. That is, under God, to have the Soveraignty and Rule over all manner of Perſons born within theſe her Realms, Dominions and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, of what eſtate, either Eccleſiaſtical or Temporal, ſoever they be, <hi>ſo as no other forreign Power ſhall or ought to have any Superiority over them.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. You heard, what Sir <hi>Orlando Bridgman</hi> underſtood by that Great Title, of <hi>Imperial</hi> Crown. Now take notice of another In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of it, from Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in that Admonition, now quoted. <hi>Imperial</hi> Crown—That under God, (and not under the Pope, or any foreign Prince or Potentate) ſo as no other <hi>foreign Power</hi> ſhall or ought to have any Superiority over them. And it is rational to conceive, that ſuch as the King, or Monarch is,<note place="margin">So ſaith Lord Keeper <hi>Bridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> in the Book quoted.</note> ſuch is his Crown: The King of <hi>England</hi> is not an Abſolute King, but in contradiſtinction to all foreign Princes and Powers, none of whom hath any power over him, he is ſubject to none, therefore the Title of Imperial Crown, adds nothing of Real power to the King, but a glorious Epithet, ſignifying, that he holds not his Crown of any other forreign Prince or Power. So is the Monarchy of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> deſcribed by that famous Counſellour Sir <hi>Thomas Smith.</hi>— <q>At the laſt the Realm of <hi>England</hi> grew into one Monarchy. Neither were any one of thoſe Kings, neither he who firſt had all, took any Inveſtiture at the hand of the Emperor of <hi>Rome,</hi> or of any other ſuperior or foreign Prince, but held of God to Himſelf, and by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94791:12"/>his Sword, his People and Crown, <hi>acknowledging no Prince on Earth his ſuperior, and ſo it is kept and holden at this day.</hi> 
                     <bibl>De Repub. Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum. c.9. Sect. I.</bibl>
                  </q>
And when our Writers ſpeak of the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of the Kings of <hi>England</hi> in oppoſition to the Pope, and his Uſurpation, they ſpeak of the Crown as an Imperial Crown, and the Kingdom as an Empire. So Sir <hi>John Davis,</hi> in the Caſe of Praemunire, or Conviction of <hi>Solar.</hi> 4 <hi>Jac.</hi> upon the Statute of the 16 R. 2. c. 5. publiſhed by Sir <hi>John Pettus.</hi>— <q>Yet if we look into the Stories and Record of theſe two Imperial King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, we ſhall find that if theſe Laws of Proviſion and Praemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire had not been made, they had loſt the name of <hi>Imperial,</hi> and of Kingdoms too, and had been long ſince made Tributary Provinces to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  </q> or rather part of St. <hi>Peter's Patrimony,</hi> or <hi>Demeſn, &amp;c. pag.</hi> 6, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
And L. Ch. Juſtice <hi>Cook</hi> Rep. of the Eccleſiaſtical Laws, printed with the former, deſcribes the Empire of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> in theſe words. <q>And therefore by the Ancient Laws of this Realm, this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England</hi> is an Abſolute Empire and Monarchy, <hi>Conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of One Head, which is the King, and of a Body Politick, compact and compounded of many, and almoſt infinite ſeveral, and yet well-agreeing Members,</hi> &amp;c. <bibl>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 46.</bibl>
                  </q>
Obſerve, he makes not the King to be abſolute Emperor over his Subjects, giving them Edicts for Laws, and ruling them in an Imperial way, but the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> whereof the King is Head, with his Body, is an Empire. So I do, with ſubmiſſion to my Teachers, conclude, that the Crown and Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> is Imperial, that is, Independent, in reſpect of the Pope, or any other foraign Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior; but that the Crown and King is not Imperial in reſpect of the Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> giving them Laws and Edicts according to his own Will; for all our Laws are made with the Conſent of Lords and Commons.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Kings of <hi>England</hi> are Supreme Governours, next and immediately under God. But let us keep to the word Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or Adminiſtrator: There are two things in a Government, Conſtitution,<note place="margin">There a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> and <hi>Legiſlator.</hi>
                  </note> and Adminiſtration. The Fundamental Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Government, is by King, Lords and Commons. The King is not the ſole Legiſlator. Power, and <hi>Supreme Power is lodged there onely, where Legiſlation is.</hi> The Legiſlative Power is in the Parliament, the Parliament doth conſiſt of King Lords, and Commons, jointly. Hear what King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94791:12"/>in his Anſwer to the XIX Propoſitions, <hi>pag.</hi> 18. of the firſt Edition, <q>In this Kingdom the Laws are jointly made by a King, by a Houſe of Peers, and by a Houſe of Commons choſen by the People; all having free Votes, and particular Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. The Government according to theſe Laws <hi>is truſted</hi> to the King. <hi>The moſt high and abſolute Power</hi> of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> conſiſteth in the Parliament,—which repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth, and hath the Power of the whole Realm, both the Head and the Body.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Sir. <hi>Tho. Smith,</hi> De Repub. Angl. <hi>B.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1.—</bibl> And tho we acknowledg the King to be the only Supreme Governor, the very word <hi>Governor</hi> doth limit the word <hi>Supreme.</hi> For being a Governor according to Law, not made by his own Will or Authority, but by the Conſent of the three Eſtates in Parliament, he is limited as Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, to govern according to Law: And ſo being a limited Governor, his Supremacy is a limited Supremacy. He is Supreme next under God; that is, there is no Governor over him, or above him: If there were any Governor over him, he would not be Supreme. He who is Governor only according to Law, cannot of his own Will, and ſhould not follow ſuch Counſellors, as put him upon Courſes deſtructive of the Laws by which he ought to govern.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Our Supreme Governor is truſted with many Royal Prerogatives, for the Good and Welfare of the Subjects. <q>So K. <hi>Ch.</hi> I. acknowledged, in his Anſwer to the XIX Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. For our Subjects ſake, theſe Rights are veſted in us, <bibl>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 17.</bibl> The Prince may not make uſe of this high and perpetual Power, to the hurt of thoſe for whoſe Good he hath it, <bibl>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 19.</bibl>
                  </q>
Therefore he cannot command what he will, nor change the Government and Religion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom eſtabliſhed by Law, as hath been deſign'd of late.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Our Supreme Governor is ſuch a Governor, that is alſo bound to keep the Law, and is ſubject himſelf to Law. <q>There are many Caſes wherein a Subject, in maintainance of his Right, may wage Law with the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                     <bibl>ſaith Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Saunderſon,</hi> Sect. 12.</bibl>
                  </q>
And King <hi>James</hi> the 1ſt, in his Speech in the Star-Chamber, <hi>June</hi> 20. 1616. ſaid, <q>I was ſworn to maintain the Law of the Land, and therefore I had been perjur'd if I had alter'd it, <bibl>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 13.</bibl>
                  </q>
What then, if the Laws, and Government, in the Eſſentials of it, come to be chang'd?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:94791:13"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But there are ſome Ancient Lawyers, of greateſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, who ſay, <hi>Nemo preſumat de faciis ejus (Regis) diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere, nedum contra factum ejus venire.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I remember I have read thoſe words, father'd upon <hi>Bracton,</hi> by your late R. R. Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> in his Speech at <hi>Magdalen</hi> Colledg. The words of <hi>Bracton</hi> are theſe, (which either his Lordſhip had not read in the Author, or had forgotten) <hi>Nemo quidem de factis ſuis preſumat diſputare, multà fortiùs contra factum ſuum venire,</hi> l. 1. c. 8. But if he had conſidered what that venerable Author hath written in the ſame Chapter, before thoſe words, he had rather diſſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the King from that Action againſt the Colledg, than have ſerv'd him in it. <hi>Ipſe autem Rex, non debet eſſe ſub homine, ſed ſub Deo, &amp;c ſub Lege, Quia Lex facit Regem. Attribuat igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Rex Legi, quod Lex attribuit Ei, videlicet Dominationem &amp; poteſtatem. Non enim Rex ubi</hi> Dominatur voluntas, &amp; non Lex. <hi>Et quidem ſub Lege eſſe debeat, cum ſit Dei Vicarius,</hi> &amp;c. The ſame Sentences, miſrepeated by that late Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> are to be ſeen in <hi>Fleta,</hi> who flouriſhed in the ſame Age with <hi>Bracton,</hi> and gives to Poſterity the Face which the Law had in the Days of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. As Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> ſaith, in his <hi>Diſſertatio ad Fletam,</hi> immediately after thoſe words, <hi>nec contra factum ſuum venire,</hi> theſe words follow? <hi>Verum tamen in populo regendo ſuperiores habet,</hi> ut Legem per quam factus eſt Rex. <hi>Et Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſuam, viz. Comites &amp; Barones: Comites enim à Comitiva dicuntur, qui cum viderint Regem ſine fraeno, fraenum ſibi appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere tenentur, &amp;c. Temperent igitur Reges potentiam ſuam per Legem, quae fraenum eſt potentiae.</hi> l. 1. c. 17. p. 17. And <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. of that Chapter, derives, <hi>Rex non à regnando, â bene regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do nomen aſſumitur; Rex verò dum benè regit, Tyrannus verò dum populum ſuâ violatâ opprimitur dominatione.</hi> Such a Supreme Governor we acknowledg the King of <hi>England</hi> to be: And what can you infer from hence?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But the Reverend Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon</hi> ſpeaks as plainly as can be, That a mixt Monarchy is an errand Bull and Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, <hi>in adjecto.</hi> And therefore the King hath the ſole So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty of Power in himſelf, and can't be controll'd or contradicted, much leſs oppoſed by Force.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I do as freely acknowledg the Supremacy of the King of <hi>England,</hi> according to Law, and ſettled upon him by Law, as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94791:13"/>you do; and that Subjects ſhould keep in the Bounds of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and obey their Superiors for Conſcience-ſake. I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, that a mixt Monarchy is as abſurd as a Compound Simple: But yet I find our Monarchy to be a Regulated, and not an Abſolute Monarchy: And if it be compounded of the three Forms of Government, Monarchy, Ariſtocracy, and Democracy, then it is no ſuch. Bull as to be an <hi>Errand One.</hi> That it is ſuch a Monarchy, I prove by a greater Author than that Learned Writer. Look then to the Anſwer of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. to the XIX Propoſitions, ſent to him from the two Houſes to <hi>York, July</hi> 1642. <q>The Wiſdom of your Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors hath moulded this Government out of a Mixture of all three, <bibl>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 18.</bibl>
                  </q>
And let me note to you, to what the King did attribute this Conſtitution; the ſaith, <q>The Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Experience of your Anceſtors hath moulded this.</q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But when did the Wiſdom of our Anceſtors meet, and where, to mould and faſhion this Government?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>That I may not confound our Diſcourſe, I muſt firſt ſpeak to the Particulars of the former Objection, or Query, and then come to new Matter.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <q>We are bound to bear Faith and true Allegiance to the King, his Heirs and Succeſſors; and to defend him and them to the utmoſt of our Power, againſt all Conſpiracies and Attempts whatſoever, that ſhall be made againſt their Perſons, their Crown and Dignity, by reaſon or colour of any ſuch Sentence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
I pray, Sir, let me explain my ſelf to you concerning theſe things.
<list>
                     <item>1. We may, I conceive, lay down this, that the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of Power lies in the King, and three Eſtates,<note place="margin">Of our Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance.</note> or in the Parliament, conſiſting of all theſe jointly. That the Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority of Government is veſted in the King; who as he is King by Law, ſo he is obliged to govern according to it. Therefore the Power of the King is not Abſolute, in reſpect of his Subjects, nor unlimited; but tho the Limits of Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative are not ſet down, becauſe extraordinary Emergencies cannot be foreſeen nor determined, yet it is limited by Law, or elſe it would be in ſome ſenſe infinite. That it is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited, is no new Divinity, as it is no new Law.<note place="margin">See alſo <hi>Dr. Ferm.</hi> Conſe. ſatisfied.</note> 
                        <hi>Non lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimur Regibus poteſtatem illimitatam, &amp; infinitam, ut quamlibet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94791:14"/>Religionem poſſint ſubditis pro arbitrio praeſcribere; ſed poteſtatem à Deo delegatam ac proinde Regulis Legis Divinae circumſcriptam. Nam ut in Cauſis Civilibus (quamvis ſint ſuprema poteſtate ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mati) non poſſunt tamen Leges condere contra aequitatem &amp; natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, &amp;c.</hi> Rev. Dr. <hi>Ward. Determin. Regis in Regno ſuo ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma eſt ſub Deo poteſtas,</hi> p. 105. 3. And if the Power of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns be limited, ſo the Obedience of Subjects is limited alſo; for Power of Commanding, and Duty of Obeying, are of the ſame Extent.</item>
                     <item>2. Allegiance is the Duty of a Subject, to which he is bound by Law; and Allegiance is reciprocal between the King and his Subjects. <hi>Ligantia ſignificat, &amp; inde Ligantia, &amp; Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giantia, Vinculum arctius inter ſubditum &amp; Regem, utroſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem connectens: hunc ad Protectionem, &amp; juſtum Regimen, illos ad Tributa &amp; debitam ſubjectionem,</hi> &amp;c. Sir <hi>H. Spellman,</hi> Gloſſ.</item>
                     <item>3. The King is the formal and expreſs Object of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, as Supreme Governor, but the Kingdom is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Object of it, yea, and the ultimate Object of it, under God, and its Welfare and Good. And ſo I find in that great Author, Sir <hi>Hen. Spelman,</hi> v. <hi>Fidelitas,</hi> a Law of St. <hi>Edward,</hi> 
                        <q>That all People ought once a Year to confederate and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidate, like ſworn Brethren, to defend the <hi>Kingdom</hi> againſt Foreigners and Enemies, together with the King.</q>
By which I ſee the true Intereſt of the King and Kingdom is one and the very ſame; but it was our unhappineſs of late, to find the true and united Intereſt divided, and an Intereſt promoted, as contrary to the Kingdom, as Darkneſs to Light, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Idolatry, to the Goſpel of Chriſt. In the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition we are in, What was to be done but what was done? No Man in Conſcience could adhere to the King againſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Kingdom; for our Obligation and Subjection is firſt due to God, and to <hi>the King in</hi> him, and <hi>for</hi> him, (and no otherwiſe, as it is in the Prayer in the Communion Service.) If the King doth perſiſt to act contrary to God; Who can in Duty folly him, or aſſiſt him? Next to my Fidelity to my Heavenly Lord, I owe my Fidelity to the Community of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by the Law of God and of Nature, whereof I am a Member; becauſe the Community muſt be governed by righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and good Laws; and theſe Laws executed, I am next obliged to that form of Government conſtituted and agreed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94791:14"/>unto. And then, laſtly, I am obliged to the perſonal Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign the King. My Fidelity to the Community (or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, under a King) is due, by God's Law, in Nature: My Fidelity to the Perſon of the King, is by a voluntary Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, required by a poſitive Law, as King of <hi>England</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning by Law. And my natural Allegiance to the King, is to him as a King by Law, and governing by Law. Judicious Mr. <hi>Lawſon,</hi> delivers himſelf thus, concifely and rationally; <q>Fidelity to the Community is firſt due: Fidelity to it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome form of Government was the ſecond: Fidelity to it under that form, by King, Peers, and Commons, was the third: Fidelity unto the Perſon of the King is the laſt, and preſuppoſeth the former. Whoſoever underſtands, and takes them (that is, the Oaths of Supremacy and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance) otherwiſe, perverts the true meaning of them, and makes them unlawful. <bibl>
                              <hi>Politica Sacra, &amp; Civilis,</hi> c. 15. p. 125.</bibl>
                        </q>
 An Anſwer to the Learned Author of the <hi>Rights of the Kingdom,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hobs, <hi>p.</hi> 17.</note> gives us ſeveral Ancient Laws, obliging the Subject to Allegiance to <hi>the Kingdom,</hi> with the King, in the Days of Old.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. The Oaths of Allegiance were made to the King, as a Proteſtant, in a direct oppoſition to the Pope, and his uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Juriſdiction, and Power. And though Fidelity and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is due to Kings of the Romiſh Faith, yet <hi>how theſe Oaths can be</hi> taken under ſuch a King, I do not underſtand; Except I declare what the King ought to be, <hi>viz.</hi> the only Supreme Governour in his Kingdoms and Dominions, and that the Pope ought not to have any Juriſdiction, Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or Spiritual, when I am ſure enough the King doth own ſuch a Juriſdiction, by profeſſing that Religion: How can I ſwear to maintain the Prehemencies and Authorites granted or annexed to the Imperial Crown, when he hath parted with the Preheminence and Authority, of being ſupreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in all Cauſes, to the Pope? This would be to ſwear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Him, and not for Him. I look upon it as a Priviledg that I had no occaſion to be called to take thoſe Oaths in his time; It was one of his beſt Acts of Indulgence to diſpence with the taking of them, though the Deſign was to open a Door for Popery to come in.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:94791:15"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But though you took not the Oaths in the late King's Time, you took them in the Time of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d,</hi> and were obliged to <hi>James</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> as his Heir and Succeſſor, and ſo to the Heirs and Succeſſors you owe Allegiance, Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Defence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I do confeſs I do, to Heirs and Succeſſors that are Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, <hi>by theſe Oaths,</hi> and to no other Heirs or Succeſſors but ſuch as are Proteſtants, or of the Reformed Religion, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to Popery? <q>The Oath of Supremacy was deviſed to put a Difference between Papiſts, and them of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; ſo was this Oath (of Allegiance) to put a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the civilly Obedient Papiſts, and the perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Diſciples of the Powder-Treaſon, ſaith the Learned K. <hi>Jam.</hi> I. <bibl>
                        <hi>Apology for the Oath of Allegiance,</hi> p. 46, 47.</bibl>
                  </q> 
By taking theſe Oaths, I teſtified my ſelf to be a Proteſtant, and a Loyal Subject; but it was to no other than a Proteſtant King in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Proteſtant Heirs and Succeſſors in time to come. I ſay, only to Proteſtant Succeſſors and Heirs, becauſe, elſe the main Suppoſition of thoſe Oaths is laid aſide. For a Popiſh Succeſſor and Heir, doth not maintain his own Preheminence, nor honour of his Imperial Crown, for he becomes a Subject to the Papal Spiritual Juriſdiction, if not Temporal alſo. I can only declare, He ought to be Supreme in his Realm; But cannot teſtify and declare that <hi>He is,</hi> for he hath made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Subject to Papal Juriſdiction. The Suppoſition of the Oath of Allegiance is, that the King of <hi>England</hi> is an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and for Hereſy Excommunicated; and being Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, he may be depoſed, and his Subjects diſcharged of their Allegiance, and ſeveral other things dangerous to Him. But we cannot ſuppoſe the Pope will Excommunicate, and Depoſe, or do any other Papal Acts, againſt a Son of his Church. I know the Oaths are required by Law in many Caſes, and were taken by many worthy Men in the Reign of the late King, but can be juſtified no further, than as they contain and oppoſition againſt Popery, as I conceive in my ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Opinion.</p>
               <p>But letting this paſs, (tho the taking of God's Name in vain, in any part of an Oath, is a great Sin, and muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of): The words are <hi>Heirs and Succeſſors;</hi> if there be an Heir of the Body of the King to ſucceed, or a Succeſſor, in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94791:15"/>want of an Heir, the Oath ſuppoſeth a Failure in the Line, but not in the Succeſſion. No Man is called upon to take theſe Oaths, till there be a Succeſſor actually apparent and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged. My Oath to the King, and his Heirs and Succeſſors, binds me then to no more, than to actual Allegiance to the King in Being, and to a preparation of mind, to bear Faith and Allegiance to his Heirs and Succeſſors, when they aſcend the Throne. But yet let it be remembred, that in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Oaths of Allegiance, there is no mention of Heirs and Succeſſors, but only to the King in being. See the Oath of Allegiance to K. <hi>Will.</hi> I. in Sir. <hi>H. Spelm.</hi> Gloſſary, <hi>Ver. Legantia.</hi> and to <hi>Hen.</hi> II. out of <hi>Nubrigenſes.</hi> And many Inſtances to this purpoſe are brought by the Learned Author of the Rights of the Kingdom, <hi>p.</hi> 33. &amp;c. And tho, Sir, you will not be pleaſed to hear more of this; If the Crown of <hi>England</hi> had been Hereditary, there had been no need of ſwearing Subjects to the Heirs and Succeſſors, in the time of the King Regnant. And one Reaſon, (as Rev. Mr. <hi>Lawſon</hi> thinks) why theſe words, Heirs and Succeſſors, were put into the Oath, was, <q>That ſeeing Election and Succeſſion was uſually in a Line, it was intended to exclude Pretenders, and all Power of the Pope, or any other, to diſpoſe of the Crown, when the former Poſſeſſor was removed, or deceaſed. <bibl>
                        <hi>Polit. ſacra &amp; Civilis,</hi> p. 215.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And I pray, Sir, give me the meaning of thoſe words in the Oath of Supremacy.— <q>And to my Power ſhall Aſſiſt and defend all Juriſdictions, Priviledges, Preheminencies, and Authorities, <hi>Granted,</hi> or belonging to the King's High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, his Heirs and Succeſſors, or <hi>united and annexed to</hi> the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Crown of the Realm.</q>
By whom were theſe Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, Preheminences, and Authorities <hi>granted</hi> and Annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if not by Parliament, the Repreſentatives of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of <hi>England?</hi> And if by Parliament then, I leave you to infer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>Do you inſinuate, as tho you thought any Prerogatives were granted by Parliaments? If ſo, then you ſeem to derive the Authority of the Crown from the People originally, which Opinion is to be abhorred; and tends to diſſolve the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If ſo, again, you ſeem to make the Crown to ſit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Severaign's Head by Compact and Election. Whereas,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94791:16"/>the Excellent Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon,</hi> doth, by a Chain of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, expoſe the vanity of ſuch Imaginations to be hiſt or laught at, <hi>Pref. Sect.</hi> 16.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>You put me upon ſearching into many hard things, which I will enquire into, as being deſirous to know the truth, that I may more chearfully perform Obedience. And firſt I deny your Conſequence, that if Power be derived from the People, then will it follow that the People may change the Government? Becauſe the Government being ſettled, we are all obliged to preſerve the Conſtitution, as long as we poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly can, and as long as all Degrees keep in their places, and act according to the Laws of the Conſtitution, we cannot changes it for a Better.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As I do perceive, the Crown and Soveraignty of the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> is Hereditary, by Election. The Power and Authority is from God, who hath diſtinguiſhed Perſons, into Superiors, Inferiors, and Equals, and hath tied them to mutual Duties in the <hi>fifth</hi> Commandment. But the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent forms of Government, are made by the Wiſdom and Conſent of the Community in a Repreſentative. K. <hi>Ch.</hi> I. who was Learned, and Judicious, ſpeaks in praiſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and of our Anceſtors, and acknowledgeth it, <q>The Wiſdom and Experience of our Anceſtors, moulded this Government. And ſo this Government, as far as it was moulded by them, is an Ordinance of Man, or an Humane Creature. It was the Wiſdom of our Anceſtors, and their Wiſdoms could not at firſt find out, or make a perfect Mould; but it ſeems, tried, and mended, and in Time, by Experience and Wiſdom, caſt it into the preſent Mould.</q> 
                  <hi>Anſw. to the XIX Propoſ.</hi> as before quoted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Kings of <hi>England</hi> were Elected, and choſen to the Office and Truſt of Kingly Government. This is clear enough, from the <hi>Britiſh,</hi> through the <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> Kings, to <hi>William</hi> the Firſt, called the <hi>Conqueror;</hi> and we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive our Common Laws from the <hi>Saxons,</hi> as I am informed. I will ſhew you what the Ancient and Renowned <hi>Fleta</hi> hath left as his Judgment and Law, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>S.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>Nec à Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando dicitur, ſed a benè regendo nomen aſſumitur, Rex verò dum benè regit, Tyrannus dum populum ſuâ violatâ apprimitur domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione. Ad hoc nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> electus eſt, ut juſtitiam pariter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94791:16"/>ſibi ſubditis faciat exhibere,</hi> &amp;c. And, <hi>Sect.</hi> 14.—<hi>Ad haec enim Creatus eſt Rex &amp; Electus, ut juſticiam faciat <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Florentius Wigornienſis,</hi> that old Hiſtorian, relates, That <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> the Firſt, who united <hi>England</hi> into one Kingdom, was, <hi>Electus ab omni Anglorum Populo,</hi> of all the People of <hi>England, Edit.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>p.</hi> 355. as he was before choſen of the <hi>Mercians</hi> and <hi>Northumbrians,</hi> who deſerted King <hi>Edwin,</hi> becauſe he acted fooliſhly in the Government committed to him, <hi>p.</hi> 354. After the deceaſe of <hi>Edgar,</hi> there aroſe a great Diſſention among the chief Men of the Kingdom about the Election of a King; for ſome Elected <hi>Edward</hi> his Son, and others Elected his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Ethelred,</hi> p. 361. And to ſave the labour of looking fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you may ſee how the Succeſſion went; ſee in a brief Hiſtory of the Succeſſion printed the other Day.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Government grew by degrees into Kingdoms, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in Families, encreaſed into Vicinities, Towns, Cities, Common-Wealths and Kingdoms. And that Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was beſt, which beſt agreed with the People, and was moſt conducive to the Publick Benefit. Hear what the Admired and Learned Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> thought, <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Book</hi> I. <hi>of Eccleſ. Policy,</hi> p. 27, 29.</bibl> The Caſe of Man's Nature ſtanding as it doth, ſome kind of Regiment the Law of Nature doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; yet the Kinds thereof being many, Nature tieth not to any One, but leaveth the Choice as a thing Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. This is contrary to them that ſet up Monarchy, and Abſolute too, upon the Foundation of the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. As to the derided Contract and Conſent of the People, where and by whom, and abundance of Queſtions about it, I conceive, the words of the ſame Learned <hi>Hooker,</hi> may bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance thoſe of Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon.</hi> 
                  <q>That which we ſpake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore concerning the Power of Government, muſt be here applied to the Power of making Laws, to command whole politick Societies of Men, belongeth ſo properly unto the ſame intire Societies of Men, that for any Prince or Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, of what kind ſoever upon Earth, to exerciſe the ſame of himſelf, and not either by expreſs Commiſſion imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and perſonally received from God, or elſe by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority derived at firſt from their Conſent, upon whoſe Perſons they impoſe Laws, it is no better than meer Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94791:17"/>Laws they are not therefore, which publick Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation hath not made ſo. But Approbation not only they give, who perſonally declare their Conſent by Voice, Sign, or Act, but alſo when others do it in their Names, <hi>by Right at leaſt originally derived from them;</hi> As in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Councils, and the like Aſſemblies, <bibl>
                        <hi>B.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 28.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The many of Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon</hi>'s Queſtions may eaſily be anſwered, by deſtroying his Suppoſition, <q>That there was a great number of People, as big ſuppoſe as a Kingdom, without Government; and that theſe all muſt, in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects be equal, or elſe they may be injured by ſome who contract, and all preſent to chuſe their Governor, and give him Power to rule according to contract<note n="*" place="margin">See the ſame Suppoſition handſomly flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd by Dr. <hi>Fern.</hi> Conſc. ſatisfied, <hi>p. 9.</hi> It is no Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by whom or when the firſt Contract was made, we are ſure it was by the Light of Nature or Reaſon, in the moſt convenient way: Let us ſee how it is now, and hath been of a long time.</note>
                  </q>
Whereas, we read in our Hiſtories, that ſometimes the Nobles, ſometimes Nobles and Prelats, ſometimes the Heads of the Commons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with their King, upon Conditions to govern. But that is the moſt perfect way, which is by the three Eſtates met in Parliament, or Convention.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That there were, and are, Contracts between the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and the People, or the Community made by their Repreſentatives, is not void of ſufficient Proof. Take a few; The People of <hi>England</hi> are called the <hi>King's Liege People,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are obliged to him: And the King is alſo called the <hi>Liege King,</hi> for the ſame Reaſon, becauſe he is bound, by Contract or Covenant, to them. <hi>Dicuntin utri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ligii; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps nempe, ligius Dominus ſubdits verb Populus ligius, &amp; homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ligii.—Ligia foedus—Eigii igitus &amp; liges idem ſunt quod ligati.</hi> Spelm. <hi>Gloſſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many Inſtances might be produced of Contracts, between our Ancient Kings, and the People of <hi>England.</hi> Two ſhall ſuffice. When <hi>Suanus</hi> tyrannized over the Land, he exacted a huge Tribute of St. <hi>Edmunds-Bury;</hi> threatned to burn it, if he had it not paid him: and giving out opprobious Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage againſt that St. <hi>Edmund,</hi> at <hi>Gainsburrough,</hi> where he held a General Plea, died there in great Agony, and Fear, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the appearance of St. <hi>Edmund</hi> coming againſt him. The Daniſh Fleet choſe his Son <hi>Canutus</hi> to be King. <hi>At majores
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94791:17"/>Natu totius Angliae;</hi> The Elders, or Eldermen of all <hi>England,</hi> ſent Meſſengers, with one conſent, to <hi>Ethelred</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> (then in <hi>Normandy</hi>) ſaying, <q>That they loved, and would love none more than Him, their natural Lord, <hi>If he would more</hi> rightly govern, or more mildly handle them, than he had before.</q>
Which when he heard, he directed his Son <hi>Edward</hi> with Embaſſadors to them, and he in moſt friendly manner ſaluted the Greater, and the Leſſer of his Nation, Promiſing, <q>That he would be to them a mild and devoted Lord; that he would conſent to their Will in all Things; acquieſce in their Counſels; that he would pardon what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was reproachfully and diſgracefully ſaid of him, or his, or done contrary to him and his, <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> omnes unanimiter, &amp;c.</hi> if all would unanimouſly, and without treachery agree to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him into the Kingdom. All of them did anſwer Courteouſly or freely to theſe things. Afterwards a full Accord, or Friendſhip is confirmed on both ſides, &amp; <hi>Verbis, &amp; Pacto,</hi> both by Words and Contract. <bibl>
                        <hi>Florentius Wiger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienſis.</hi> p. 381.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The other Inſtance I give out of the ſame Hiſtorian is <hi>omni Exceptione major:</hi> it is of <hi>William</hi> the firſt, commonly called the <hi>Conqueror. William</hi> came to <hi>London</hi> with his whole Army, <hi>ut ibi in Regem ſublimaretur,</hi> that he might be advanced to be King, and was Conſecrated in an honourable manner, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing firſt</hi> (as <hi>Aldred</hi> the Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> required, or exacted of him) before the Altar of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> by Oath, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Clergy and People, <q>That he would defend the Holy Churches of God, and their Rectors, and govern all the People ſubject to Him, juſtly, and with Regal Care, and Providence; Appoint, or ordain and hold Right Law, and forbid Rapines, and unjuſt Judgments utterly, or altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <bibl>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 431.</bibl>
                  </q>
But that which goes beyond all particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, is the Coronation Oath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But concerning the Coronation Oath, I am of the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Rev. Dr. <hi>Falkner,</hi> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Chriſtian Loyalty.</hi> B. 2. c. 2. <hi>p.</hi> 423.</bibl> Let us turn to the place. <q>The Solemnity of Coronation, when the People acknowledg their King, and the King again gives the People aſſurance, that he will preſerve their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Rights and Laws, is far from intending to expreſs the King's Authority to be derived from the People by a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94791:18"/>as ſome have weakly argued; for the King is actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally King, by his Right of Inheritance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I diſtinguiſh between the ſolemnity of Coronation, (the Prince appearing in Splendor, doth excite the People to make Acknowledgments, and expreſſion of Affection, with Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the Doctor goes on) and the Queſtions propoſed to the King and the Coronation-Oath. The Argument for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Contract, is built upon the Demands made to the King, and his Oath, and the Fealty ſworn to the King. The Forms of the Coronation Oath have been divers, as you may ſee, in the moſt laborious Mr. <hi>Pryn, Epiſt. to the Reader,</hi> before his Hiſt. of K. <hi>John, Hen.</hi> 3. <hi>Edw.</hi> the I. out of the Records of the <hi>Tower,</hi> from <hi>p.</hi> 30, &amp;c. The King is obliged, as <hi>Fleta</hi> tells you. <hi>C. praedict.—Nec poteſt quis judicare in temporalibus, niſi ſolus Rex vel ſub delegatus: Ipſe nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ex virtute Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ad hoc ſpecialiter Obligatur,</hi> &amp; ideò Coronâ inſignitur, <hi>ut per judicia populum rogat ſibi ſubjectum.</hi> I follow the directions of that Learned laborious Writer, and find his Quotation out of <hi>Bracton</hi> true, <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>de Actionibus. c.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 107. <hi>S.</hi> 1, 2, 3.</bibl> The King ought in his Coronation to ſwear, and promiſe to his People ſubject to him;
<list>
                        <item>1. That he will Command, and to his Power help, that Peace be obſerved all his Time, to the Church of God, and all Chriſtian People.</item>
                        <item>2. That he will interdict Rapines, and all Iniquities, to all degrees.</item>
                        <item>3. That in all his Judgments he will command Equity and Mercy; that the Gracious and Merciful God may grant him Mercy; and that all may, through his Righteouſneſs, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a firm Peace: <hi>Ad hoc autem Creatus &amp; Electus eſt;</hi> To this End, or Office, he is Created and Choſen.</item>
                     </list>
And our Righteous Kings have look'd upon themſelves as bound to do what they promiſed and ſwore to at their Coronation.</q>
See the Quotations in that <hi>Epiſt.</hi> p. 31. And K. <hi>James</hi> the Firſt,<note place="margin">Even <hi>Dr. Fern</hi> doth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, It is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable indeed, that Things at firſt were by choice here as elſewhere. The Reſolving of Conſe. <hi>S. 4. p. 19.</hi>
                  </note> ſaid, <hi>He ſhould be perjur'd if he did not obſerve the Laws.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I diſtinguiſh between Sole Election, Conſent, and Hereditary Right by Common Law. Our Kings and Queens ſucceed by Hereditary Right, preſuppoſing an Election of the Royal Progenitors, or voluntary Conſent in the Acts of Settlement, and ſtill demanded and declared at every Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. As every King or Queen is not Elected as by a People
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94791:18"/>in abſolute Liberty, to chuſe whom they pleaſe, ſo it is not conceived to be Hereditary by Common Law, but by Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment implying the Conſent of the People. And if you would know how it was of Old, obſerve how it is now, in the moſt happy Agreement between our now moſt Gracious King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and the Collective Wiſdom and Power of the Kingdom,<note place="margin">Now our High Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> in the for-ever to be celebrated Convention. Our former wiſe Kings have thought an Act of Parliament, the beſt Deed of Settlement of the Crown: And how the Succeſſion hath been changed, is to be ſeen in that Excellent ſhort Hiſtory of the Succeſſion, come to my Hands t'other day<note n="*" place="margin">Sold by <hi>J. Robinſon</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Ch. yard.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>Let things be as they were in former Times: Let us, if we be Men of Conſcience, remember our Declaration, and the Oath, ſworn by all Officers, of the Unlawfulneſs of taking Arms againſt the King, or thoſe commiſſionated by him, upon <hi>any Pretence whatſoever:</hi> Remember your Declaration, and the words, <hi>Pretence whatſoever.</hi> What-ever Limitation the Author of <hi>the Inquiry</hi> hath put upon it, by limiting the words <hi>in all things,</hi> in the Duty of Children to their Parents. And look upon what that Good and Learned Man, Dr. <hi>Falkener,</hi> hath written at large upon that Oath, in vindication of it, in the <hi>2d</hi> Book of <hi>Chriſtian Loyalty.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Content, Sir, let us look to the Book; there it is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>In the firſt Section he tells you,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Falkener</hi> conſidered.</note> 
                  <q>There is a two-fold Declaration of Loyalty in deteſtation of ſuch Poſitions as undermine the Security of Kings and Kingdoms, required in this Realm; the one more particular, in the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, againſt depoſing Excommunicated Heretical Kings; and the other more General.</q>
Of which he ſpeaks § 2.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>We deteſt the Doctrine and Practices of the Pope and Papiſts, as much as you do. And all that the Doctor hath learnedly diſcourſed of it in that Section, doth not at all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern us; not only becauſe that is Popiſh Doctrine, and becauſe it is unlawful for the Pope to excommunicate and depoſe a Proteſtant King; but becauſe we are not guilty of Depoſing our late King <hi>Jam.</hi> II. our Caſe hath been (more briefly than it might be) declared before, to prevent the Accuſation of depoſing him.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:94791:19"/>
               <p n="1">1. The King did really depoſe himſelf from being an Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent King of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">K. <hi>Jam. 2.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed himſelf, and was not depoſed.</note> by ſubmitting to the Pope.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He diſpens'd with our taking the Oath of Allegiance, which I think I ſhould not have taken, had I been required, without a plain declaration of my Mind; for it implied a contradiction to take it to a Popiſh King.</p>
               <p n="3">3. After he deſerted his puiſſant great Army, and durſt not put his Cauſe upon a Battel, he gave one Branch of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty to the Prince of <hi>Orange, viz.</hi> the Command of his Army and Navy, and then attempted to go beyond Sea; and at laſt went, leaving his Kingdom, without Force, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, or Menace. The Illuſtrious Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the Kingdom, deſired nothing but what was their Right, as much their Right as the Crown was his.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In this Caſe what ſhall the Kingdom do? You may be ſatisfied by the Debates about Abdication and Vacancy. Muſt the Kingdom lie open to the Enemies of it? Muſt there be a <hi>Juſticium,</hi> a ſilence of the Laws, and ſtop to Juſtice and Righteouſneſs, and all things fall into unſettlement and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, to wait upon his Return? Yea, muſt the Affairs of the Proteſtant Confederates be under diſtractions, through our ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolutions? Muſt the Illuſtrious Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> go back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, loſing the Opportunities of finiſhing his Work, which God gave him, in ſo wonderful a manner? And muſt the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on give time to Papiſts for new Plots, and gathering ſtrength to do us their deſigned Miſchiefs? What will become of Trade? What Foreign Princes will treat with us, when we have none to treat with them, and give them Security? Who ſhall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, or pay our Armies, or preſerve the People from their Rudeneſs, or Violence, and Factions, if they have no Chief Commander? And have not our Peers, and Commons, as good right to preſerve and ſettle the Government now, as any of their Forefathers had? How long ſhall the Nation ſtay for this King's Return? He beſt knew the Reaſons for his deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Government; and if the Kingdom had delayed to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle it Self, he would then have, by the Counſellors of Evil, had made us ſee a greater neceſſity of having him, and wrought upon our wanting him for a Head, to go beſides our ſelves like a diſtracted People, a fooliſh People of no under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. In our Caſe we had as good Reaſon to ſettle the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94791:19"/>Government, as ever People had to put themſelves into a Form and Order. And it is an ineſtimable Mercy, that God preſented to us ſuch Royal Perſons, ſo nearly related to the Inheritance of the Crown, to fill up the Vacancy. <hi>James</hi> the <hi>2d</hi> was not depoſed, nor moleſted, neither for his Religion, as inconſiſtent as it was with the Religion, Government, and Happineſs of the Kingdom. The Accuſation of Depoſing the King, is altogether untrue; He made the Vacancy, and when it was made, it muſt be filled up. Come, Doctor, now let us follow Dr. <hi>F.</hi> to the next Section.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>There you will ſee what he ſaith of the general Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Loyalty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>So I do, <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 337, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </bibl> The more general Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment for the preſervation of the King's Safety, is that which is required by the Act of Uniformity, and enjoined up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Civil and Military Officers.</q>
The firſt Clauſe of which is, that it is not lawful, upon any pretence <hi>whatſoever,</hi> to take Arms againſt the King, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 338. The ſenſe of this is, no more than what the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Eminent Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, hath conſtantly acknowledged. <hi>Homil. of Obed.</hi> part. 2. Can. of 1640. <hi>&amp; Judiciam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitat is Oxonienſis.</hi> The Doctor goes on to give ſome explication of the Oath, <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>N.</hi> 3.</bibl> This Clauſe being framed and enjoin'd by an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Parliament, not without reſpect to the diſloyal and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Proceedings in this Nation, and tendred to Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Subjects, and relating particularly <hi>to the King,</hi> not inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely <hi>to any King,</hi> can bear no other rational Conſtruction, than to condemn the <hi>Engliſh Subjects</hi> taking Arms againſt their Natural Sovereign, the King of <hi>England.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though the like Attempts againſt any other Kings, who enjoy Soveraign Authority, are equally blameleſs in their Subjects; yet this Poſition doth not aſſert <hi>the utter unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of taking Arms, amongſt other Nations, againſt him who hath the Title of King, if he doth not therewith en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Right of Supreme Government, which our Kings have and exerciſe. And therefore in ſuch a Conſtitution, as the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> was, and <hi>Tabrobana,</hi> &amp;c. we are not concerned, <bibl>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 339.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>—The true Friends of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have been free from diſloyal Actions and Aſſertions, <bibl>
                        <hi>N.</hi> 4.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:94791:20"/>He repeats ſeveral pretences for War, but all unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir, I am reſolved to be brief with you; Therefore ſhall make ſome ſhort Remarks.
<list>
                     <item>1. I note, He grants the poſition holds of the K. of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe he <hi>hath and exerciſeth Soveraign Authority.</hi> Why Dr. <hi>Falkner</hi> ſhould be honoured, who ſaith as much as <hi>Calvin</hi> did; yet <hi>Calvin</hi> is commonly branded, and Dr. <hi>F.</hi> admired and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured; ſee <hi>Calv. Inſtit. cap. ultimo. L.</hi> 4. <hi>Sect.</hi> 31. doth ſhew us the power of Prejudice.</item>
                     <item>2. The reaſon why our Kings muſt not be reſiſted is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have <hi>Soveraign Authority.</hi> Which really is but a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Soveraignty of Adminiſtration, and not of Legiſlation. The Law makes the King to be Supreme Governor, and not ſole Legiſlator: and it hath been debated, Whether the King can refuſe to ſign ſuch Bills as have paſt both Houſes, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Order of the Houſes? His Power of Calling and Diſſolving Parliaments at his own Pleaſure, hath been deemed an Uſurpation upon the Rights and Liberties of the Kingdom. K. <hi>Ch.</hi> I. in his Anſwer. to the <hi>xix Prop.</hi> confeſſeth, <q>In this Kingdom the Laws are jointly made by a King, by a Houſe of Peers, and by a Houſe of Commons choſen by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, all having free Votes, and particular Priviledges: The Government according to theſe Laws is truſted to the King.</q>
You ſee then, what a Soveraign Prince our King is, only in ſome reſpect.</item>
                     <item>3. Another Reaſon againſt taking Arms, and for the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Power of Kings, is, becauſe the <hi>jus Gladii</hi> is in the Hand of the King, determined by the Word of God, as Bp <hi>Saunderſon</hi> affirms, <hi>Pref. Sec.</hi> 15. and is determined to belong to the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> as Dr. <hi>Falkner</hi> pleads, <hi>p.</hi> 347. Be it ſo; yet this is far alſo from the preſent Caſe truly ſtated. The late Invaſion and Inſurrection was not to take the Power of the Sword from the King, nor to deprive him of that Authority which he had from God, and the Laws. The Power of the Sword and Militia, is not intruſted in the King's Hand for the Deſtruction, but Protection of his Subjects. The Office of the King, and the uſe of the Sword, is declared to be for the puniſhment of Evil-Doers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. But what? when the Sword of the Magiſtrate is abuſed againſt a Kingdom's Right
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94791:20"/>and Safety? The Militia which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, in that place, is a Power to Puniſh, and to take Vengeance upon Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers according to their Crimes. And the Sword being the Inſtrument of the ſoreſt and higheſt degree of Puniſhment, which is Capital Puniſhment, comprehends under it all degrees of Puniſhments. And this Power of the Sword, which is chiefly placed in the Hand of the Supreme Magiſtrate, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed in the Hands of all inferior Magiſtrates, and Officers, that adminiſter Juſtice, and puniſh Offenders. What is this to the raiſing of Armies? maintaining ſtanding Armies?<note place="margin">Diſpoſing, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to have them made Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Men by falſe Returns.</note> diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Military Officers into places of Civil Government? and to debauch all places whereever they come, and to oppreſs the Nation? And here's another Conſideration worthy your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, That a King that maintains Arbitrary Power by the Sword againſt Law, and ſtanding Force in Times of Peace, turns the Civil Government into a military; and that is not the Government of <hi>England.</hi> That which ſome ſpeak, that the King of <hi>England</hi> hath <hi>Merum Imperium,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Merum Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium, <hi>What?</hi>
                        </note> will do us no Hurt, if rightly underſtod. <hi>Gladius indicat, illos, ut Juriſperiti loqui ſolent, imperium habere merum.</hi> What's that? <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpianus ait, illud eſſe merum imperium quod habet poteſtatem Gladii, ad ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madvertendum in Homines facineroſos. Peter Martyr</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> ch. 13. If this right uſe of the Sword, or avenging and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power were duly obſerved; what Work would it make among them who wear the Sword? The Conteſts that have been in this Kingdom about the Power of the Militia, and the uſe that hath been made of it, is a matter of doleful remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.<note place="margin">The Declaration of the Lords and Commons, <hi>July 1.42.</hi> A Second Remonſtrance, <hi>Jan. 16.42.</hi> The King's Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff of <hi>Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi>
                        </note> (which was diſputable before, and undetermin'd) was declared to be in the King, the Edg of the Sword was turned againſt a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant State to ſwallow it up, if they could, is not forgotten. And how we were oppreſt with Royal Aids, and vaſt Paiments, to maintain that Sword, is felt to this day. <q>If the King alone hath the Power of the Sword, the Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in Parliament have the Power of the Purſe, the Sinews of War and Peace, as King <hi>Ch.</hi> I. acknowledged,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>VVhitlock</hi>'s Memorials. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1642.</hi> And at the Treaty at <hi>Uxbridg, 1644 p. 124.</hi>
                           </note> 
                           <bibl>Anſw. to the xix. <hi>Propoſ.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                        </q>
And as long as our Kings adviſe with their Parliaments about War and Peace, as they were wont to do, as that Learned Sir <hi>Robert Cotton</hi> proves, in his Treatiſe on that Argument, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1621. it muſt be our Fault, and God's
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94791:21"/>Judgment upon us, if the Sword do hurt us. But how God hath vouchſafed us that Mercy, in diſpoſing of the Crown and Sword, that we ſhall not fear the Sword, nor grudg to pray Tribute to them that are the Miniſters of God for Good.</item>
                     <item>4. All that the worthy Doctor ſpeaks of Fanatick Notions and Aſſertions, and of the War between the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, belongs not to this preſent Caſe, any further, than the Common Reaſon of both is concerned in them.</item>
                     <item>5. Thoſe Caſes in which both <hi>Grotius</hi> and <hi>Barclay</hi> affirm, that a King may be reſiſted, are with the Doctor but imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Caſes, which for the ill Conſequences of Miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, are not to be ſuppoſed.</item>
                     <item>6. He at large ſhews what ſecurity the People of <hi>England</hi> have, for their Liberties and Religion, ſo that they need not fear any Extremities to drive them to take up Arms.</item>
                     <item>7. There is ſomething that comes near our Caſe, in <hi>p.</hi> 517. Firſt, <q>That the Agreement of the whole Body of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or the chief and greater part thereof, can give no ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Authority for ſuch an enterpriſe (as taking Arms againſt the Soveraign, when oppreſſed by him) becauſe, ſaith he, the <hi>whole Community</hi> are Subjects, as well as the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons thereof. And with eſpecial reſpect to this Kingdom, I have obſerved, that the Laws declare it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, for the two Houſes of Parliament, though jointly, to take Arms againſt the King.</q>
Here are ſome Miſtakes delivered by the worthy Doctor.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <note place="margin">What a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity is.</note>(1.) He ſaith, that the Community are Subjects. A Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity as ſuch, is the Subject of a Common-Wealth, in a ſtate of Freedom, not formed into a Government. The <hi>Majeſtas Realis</hi> is in the Community, and the Community is one Perſon in Fiction of Law, and is <hi>Perſona conjuncta,</hi> as the <hi>Civilians</hi> ſpeak. So Reverend Mr. <hi>Lawſon,</hi> Anſwer to <hi>Hobs,</hi> p. 21. <hi>&amp; Polit. Sacra &amp; Civilis;</hi> A Community is the Matter of a Common-Wealth, <hi>c.</hi> 15, 206. A Community contains in it virtually all the Forms and Degrees of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Governours, that ariſe out of it. A Community, as ſuch, is no Subject. But if the Doctor mean by a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, all the Common People ſubjected by their own Conſent to a Soveraign, or Governor, then they are Subjects indeed,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:94791:21"/>as contradiſtinguiſhed from Superiors. But if all, or the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the People, (by which I do not underſtand the Vulgar) Peers and Commons, perceive the Conſtitution to be in apparent hazard of being deſtroyed, what they act in the neceſſary defence of the Government, and Fundamental Laws, and for their preſervation, they do not <hi>act as meer Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> but <hi>as one Party</hi> in Covenant and Contract with him, who threatneth to bring them to Confuſion, by deſtroying their Government.</item>
                           <item>(2.) It doth not follow, that becauſe both Houſes cannot take Arms againſt the Soveraign, therefore the whole People, or the greateſt part of the People, (among whom we include the wiſeſt and the beſt Part, and the Nobility of all Degrees) cannot in ſuch a Caſe, as ours lately was, take Arms: For tho a Parliament be entruſted to act for the People, in thoſe Affairs to which they are called and ſummoned, yet not with all the Rights and Liberties of the People. But now, here is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Convention, and the Repreſentatives of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in it, have an extraordinary Truſt, even that of form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us again, and ſettling us upon the beſt Foundation. And for this Reaſon, though this Convention wanted the uſual Call, by the King's Writ, it is one of the greateſt Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that ever was, and its Acts of greater Authority, in the extent of it, than any ordinary Parliament; and therefore the People of <hi>England</hi> are concluded by them in what they do. The Nation was generally ſenſible of approaching Ruin; they knew the King had left his Government, and willingly and freely elected their Repreſentatives, to do the beſt in their Wiſdom for the Kingdom's good. And the Conſtitution and Government is not changed, only the Perſons of our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governors.</item>
                           <item>(3.) Parliaments, and their Powers, have been much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cried, and debaſed, eſpecially of late Years. But though every Individual be a Subject, and the whole Body ſtile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the King's Subjects; yet, as a Parliament, they have a part in the Legiſlation, and therefore an eſſential part of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion in them; and as making Laws, they are above them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as obeying Laws.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>8. The Doctor inſtanceth in one Caſe, <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>p.</hi> 542.</bibl> Whether if a Supreme Governor ſhould, according to his own Pleaſure,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94791:22"/>and contrary to the eſtabliſhed Laws, and his Subjects Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, actually engage upon the deſtroying and ruining a conſiderable part of his People, they might not defend themſelves by Arms?</q> (yet this is packt up among No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and not to be ſuppoſed).
But, <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>p.</hi> 544.</bibl> 
                           <hi>If ever any ſuch</hi> ſtrange Caſe as is propoſed <hi>ſhould happen in the World, I confeſs it would have its great Difficulties;</hi> and quotes <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> that in this <hi>ultimo neceſſitatis praeſidio,</hi> as the laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, Defence is not to be condemned, provided the Care of the Common Good be preſerved. And if this be true, it muſt be upon this Ground, that ſuch attempts of ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, do, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> exclude a diſclaiming the governing thoſe Perſons as Subjects, and conſequently of being their Prince or King. And then the Expreſſions of our <hi>Publick Declaration</hi> and Acknowledgment would ſtill be ſecured, that it is not lawful, upon any <hi>Pretence whatſoever, to take Arms againſt the King.</hi>
                        </q>
That is, at laſt the Doctor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth ſuch a King to be no King. Whether this be not the Caſe, or much like to that we were in, I refer it to all that know the Motions of the late King. Did he not act to the deſtruction of Property? He might as juſtly have filled all our Churches with Popiſh Prieſts; yea, and our Houſes with Inhabitants, as ſome Colledges in the Univerſities. Did he not go as far and as faſt as he could, to deſtroy our Religion, which is our deareſt Property? And what would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of our Liberties, if a pack'd Parliament could have been made, and the Popiſh Lords have ſate in the Houſe of Lords? And what of our Perſons and Lives, if we had not been delivered by an extraordinary Providence? And I will add but this under this Head, That all the Gentlemen that I have diſcourſed with, who took up Arms, profeſs they would never have taken Arms againſt the King ruling by Law, as he was bound to do; but look'd upon him as no King, <hi>i. e.</hi> no Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal King of <hi>England</hi> in the exerciſe of his Power; and that there was no other way left for them to preſerve themſelves, our Laws and Religion.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But this doth ſtill ſtick with me, that we declared, or ſwore, That it was unlawful to take up Arms upon <hi>any Pretence whatſoever,</hi> therefore not upon this <hi>Pretence, or for this Cauſe;</hi> or any other real or Imaginary, either this, or any that can be imagined poſſible.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:94791:22"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The evil Deſign of framing that Oath, to bring the Nation tame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power and Popery.</note>I muſt ſay leſs upon this Head than I have to ſay. I am extreamly deceived,
<list>
                     <item>1. If Popery was not deſign'd, to be either made the topping Profeſſion of the Nation, or ſo far countenanced and upheld, that it would be in a fair way to be reſtored, as the Religion of the Court and Country, when that Act was made.</item>
                     <item>2. This could never be, but by the Arbitrary Power of the King.</item>
                     <item>3. To ſet up and maintain that, the ſole Power of the Militia is put into the Hand of the King.</item>
                     <item>4. The War of the Parliament againſt the King, is made Rebellion by Law.</item>
                     <item>5. All thoſe things had been inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſerve the Deſign of introducing Popery, which could not come in but by Arbitrary Power, unleſs an Oath be devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and impoſed, to tie the Hearts and Hands of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject from thinking to act, or acting againſt the Armed Force of Arbitrary Power.</item>
                  </list>
And, laſtly, no word was large e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to comprehend all poſſible Cauſes, or Reaſons of Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, but <hi>whatſoever.</hi> Do the Pope's Creatures what they they will, we are tied up, by, <hi>upon any Pretence whatſoever,</hi> to look upon our Miſeries coming on, and paſſively to lie down at the Feet of Popiſh Majeſty, <hi>i. e.</hi> cruel Tyranny, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by become Vaſſals to the Triple Crown.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Senſe of the Declaration of Non-reſiſtance.</note>Sir, I have ſubſcribed the Declaration of my Conſent to that which was required as a formal Oath of all Officers, Civil and Military; thinking it was but Reaſon and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to give the King, as a lawful Governor, ſecurity in his Throne: But the ſenſe I had of it was to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; I do believe it is not lawful, upon <hi>any Pretence whatſoever,</hi> or from any Cauſe, or Reaſon pretended, for Subjects to take Arms againſt the King, my lawful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, (for to ſuch a King we are ſubjected) and that I do abhor that traiterous Poſition, of taking Arms, by his Authority, againſt his Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are <hi>legally</hi> commiſſioned by him,<note place="margin">See, if you pleaſe, an Enquiry into the Oath requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all the Non-Con. by an Act made at <hi>Oxford;</hi> by that wiſe and worthy Man, Mr <hi>John Corbet.</hi>
                  </note> (all other Commiſſions that are not legal, being really none of the Commiſſions of the King of <hi>England,</hi> who is bound to govern accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law) in the legal purſuance of legal Commiſſions; and that I will not at any time endeavour any alteration of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, either in Church or State, <hi>by any unlawful ways.</hi> And more than this, no King that means the good of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, can deſire; and this a peaceable Subject may conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94791:23"/>give, if the King require it, for his Satisfaction. But now, if a King act contrary to the Laws, not by a particular Act, or Acts only, by which many private Subjects are inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or oppreſt, but to the changing the Fundamental Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and overturning it; then when the Cauſe is not a pretended Cauſe, framed by Jealouſy, or uncharitable Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitions of the King and his Miniſters, whether the Body, and Majority of the Kingdom, may not, in an Extremity, appeal to the ſupreme determination of God by the Sword, and vindicate the Right which they have to their Religion and Liberties, is a Caſe wherein it appears, even by Dr. <hi>Falkener,</hi> that the King is no King; and by Conſequence, the People which before were Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to the King, while he acted as King in a legal manner, are no further ſubject; and ſo the Oath is not violated, but ſtands good. The word <hi>Whatſoever,</hi> is intended in the largeſt ſenſe, and is ſo uſed in the Canons of 1640. and the Writings of ſeveral Men,<note place="margin">When a King goes about to ſet up a new Form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, contrary to the Rights of the People, the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as a Party in Contract and Covenant, and ſtill willing to perform their part, take Arms as a Party to maintain their Rights, which are invaded, and do not rebel as Subjects. So that the People of <hi>England</hi> are conſiderable, as a Party in a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Contract with the King, as Subjects.</note> as well as Dr. <hi>Ealkener.</hi> But then, I ask, Whether the King of <hi>England</hi> may act and do, beyond and contrary to the Laws of his Government, not in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Inſtances, to the particular Injury of ſome private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but againſt the Foundations of the Government, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, Peace, Welfare, Property, Liberty, and Safety of the whole Proteſtant, and greateſt part of his Subjects, be to be deemed the lawful King of <hi>England,</hi> as he was, or would be held and reputed to be, if he ruled as a ſworn King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And then, Whether the People of <hi>England</hi> are by the Laws ſubjected to an Arbitrary, Jeſuited King, or to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and Regulated King? Whether the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> are bound to whatſoever a King pleaſeth to do, ſet up, and command? or to thoſe things only which are commanded them by Law? If the Laws be the Rule and Meaſure of their Obedience, and thoſe Laws no other than what were made by their own implied Conſents, then the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> have not in this Extraordinary Action, broken the Bonds of their Subjection, but acted for their own Preſervation, as a People that were never bound to an Arbitrary Abſolute King. If the Parliament that enacted that Law that preſcribes this Oath, did intend to bind all thoſe Perſons enjoined to take it, to an unlimited Obedience to all manner of Arbitrary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions and Commands whatſoever of the King, then they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:94791:23"/>allowed to the King ſcope enough to run out into all Exceſs of Arbitrarineſs, and did by that betray the Kingdom to the Will of a King, be he Papiſt, or Tyrant.<note place="margin">Did they intend to bind them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Poſterity from taking Arms, even when a King ſhall go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to change the Legal Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and change the Government? If they did not, then in this Caſe the Oath bindeth not. That they did not, ſeems plain by the Oath, which was for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Government, and againſt the alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of it.</note> But this we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think to be in their Minds, (though there was a great number in Favour and Penſion to ſerve the ſecret Deſigns of the Court). But if they intended no more than the Safety of a Legal King, acting Legally, from ill Principles and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of bad Men, then the Note of Univerſality <hi>whatſoever,</hi> was never intended to ſubject the Kingdom to Arbitrary Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion; and then it will follow, that they who took this Oath, are no further bound, than to an Univerſal Obedience to the lawful Commands of the King, and are not guilty of Perjury by their late taking Arms, for they did not deſign to break the Yoke of Government by Rebellion. Not only the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Enquiry into the Bounds of Obedience, but alſo the moſt Reverend Arch-biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> in his Treatiſe of the <hi>Power of a Prince, and Subjection and Obedience,</hi> doth interpret the Note of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality All, Epheſ.</hi> 5.24. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.20. with a limitation, <hi>p.</hi> 143, 145.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But thoſe Commands are Affirmative; and this Oath is Negative, <hi>It is not lawful upon any Pretence whatſoever,</hi> binds at all Times, and to a total univerſal abſtinence from taking Arms. And thoſe Commands require Active Obedience with a limitation; and if we cannot actually obey, we muſt ſuffer, and not rebel, but bear even with a Tyrant; for the Laws have prohibited the Subjects to take up Arms, they have no Law that makes it lawful in any Caſe to take up Arms, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt be Paſſive. The Law is againſt Arms, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is unlawful; they have no right to the Sword, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is unlawful for them to take it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">As Subjects they may not, but as a Party, I ask you, why they may not?</note>I cannot ſpeak to every Branch of your Objection. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, what I have ſaid, I am in reaſon conſtrained to think and ſpeak, that the late King acting as he did, did not act as King, and that his Attempts were growing more intollerable; and that as there is no Proviſion in any Laws for the Peoples taking of Arms, ſo there is none which forbids them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Government, the Legiſlative Power, and Religion eſtabliſhed. There is no Law, nor Right, to bear out the King in doing as he did. He broke the Foundations firſt, and <hi>in reaſon,</hi> if the King may defend his Soveraignty from the Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:94791:24"/>of his Rebellious Subjects; ſo the ſeveral Degrees and Ranks of the Kingdom may defend the Government from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing changed, and their Properties, Liberties, Religion, and Lives from being deſtroyed. If a King ſhall ſet himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Conſtitution, and the Publick Good, he is no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that King to whom the Laws oblige us: And is it not plain to every Man, that ſeeing he could not have his way in Governing, or rather Diſſolving, he will no longer abide in the Kingdom? To ſuppoſe that the Laws would provide in what Caſes a King may turn Tyrant, and allow him to turn the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia againſt the Kingdom; and in what Caſes the Kingdom may take the Sword againſt the King, is to ſuppoſe ſuch a Law, as would be inconſiſtent with the Conſtitution: For as the King would never paſs an Act that ſhould make it lawful for Subjects to riſe in Arms againſt him; ſo it is not to be thought, that the Lords and Commons ſhould conſent to ſuch a Law as would enable the King to deſtroy the Government, Religion and Laws: The Conſent of King and Parliament in not to be ſuppoſed to make ſuch a Law, for one againſt the other; and without the conſent of both Parties there could be no Law. And ſuch a Law would not prove ſafe to the Government which is preſerved by Union: As the Subjects run the hazard of Life and Eſtate if they rebel, ſo the King doth run the hazard of his Crown, if he uſurp, and make himſelf to be what the Law hath not made him, but directly contrary.</p>
               <p>To conclude this Head. How many Violations had we been guilty of? even of all the Bonds of Nature and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if the Papiſts, and their Loyal Friends, had not been op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed at this Time. And though in this Caſe, it is lawful for a People, a free People, by the Conſtitution, to preſerve Themſelves and Poſterity from Slavery and Idolatry, yet it is unlawful for Subjects, as far as they are Subjects, to rebel againſt their King; and it had been happy, that Oath had never been enjoined, if any took it ignorantly, and raſhly, or brake it in their Hearts intentionally; or were actually the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of promoting Arbitrary Power, and Popery by it; or had any Deſign againſt the King's Dignity, out of Revenge, or for private E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds; the Lord grant unto them Repentance for the forgiveneſs of their Sin, and cleanſe the Land from the guilt of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:94791:24"/>multitudes of Oaths, not well underſtood, nor kept.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But we know the Scripture is plain againſt Reſiſtance, and we have many Examples againſt Reſiſtance, and for Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Obedience. And our <hi>Homilies</hi> condemn it, and the Friends of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have always been Guiltleſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Shew me, if you can, any thing in Scripture, Precept, or Example, that condemns ſuch an Action as this was, in the Circumſtances of Perſons, and Cauſes. The <hi>Homilies</hi> do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt much upon the Example of <hi>David.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>David</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</note> I allow what they teach: But I will make the Caſe worſe than <hi>David's</hi> was. Had <hi>Saul</hi> brought in Foreign Forces, and turn'd his Strength againſt the Kingdom, and done all after the manner of the King, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. it had been utterly unlawful for <hi>David,</hi> and all the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to take Arms againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> or depoſe Him, for there was a Law of God binding them to make him King, whom the Lord ſhould chooſe, as he choſe <hi>Saul.</hi> See the 17th of <hi>Deut.</hi> 14, 15. The Caſe of <hi>David,</hi> and ours, differ as much as the Caſe of a private Subject and a free People, as we were, when the King ſet Himſelf to do as he did. <hi>David,</hi> though appointed to be King, was but a private and particular Subject under <hi>Saul;</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> was nominated and appointed King by God himſelf, and it was God's expreſs Law, <hi>Thou ſhalt in any wiſe ſet him King over thee, whom the Lord thy God ſhall chooſe,</hi> Deut. 17.15. And when <hi>David</hi> gave this Reaſon, why he would not do what his Party would have had him do, he ſaid; <hi>God forbid I ſhould do this thing unto my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the Lord's Annointed, to ſtretch forth mine Hand againſt Him, ſeeing he is the Annointed of the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 24.6. <hi>His autem Verbis David tantùm ſpectabat Inſtitutum Dei. David</hi> regarded the Appointment of God.—<hi>Ergo injuſſu Dei non debeo eum dejicere,</hi> Therefore without God's Command, I ought not depoſe him. <hi>Pet. Martyr</hi> on the words—And that Learned and Reverend Man anſwering the Reaſons of ſome who thought <hi>David</hi> might lawfully have killed <hi>Saul,</hi> gives the Reaſons why he could not. They ſay, <hi>David</hi> was King. <hi>Eſto,</hi> be it ſo ſaith <hi>P. Martyr;</hi> but he was not publickly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>augurated. <hi>Vim vi repellere licet,</hi> ſay they, <hi>Fateor,</hi> I confeſs it is lawful to repel Force with Force, ſaith <hi>P. Martyr. Sed inculpatâ tutelâ</hi> with an innocent or blamleſs Defence, as <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilians</hi> ſpeak; that is to ſay, if they cannot fly, nor defend
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94791:25"/>themſelves any other way. But <hi>David</hi> ſaw he might defend himſelf another way, <hi>David ergo non potuit ullo jure Saulem occidere. David</hi> could not kill <hi>Saul</hi> by any Law or Right, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when he ſaw that would tend to the Overthrow of the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">If it was lawful for <hi>David</hi> to take Arms, and head a Party for his own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, why not for <hi>England</hi> as one Man? And then how can this Oath be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids that (in your ſenſe of it) which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture allows, and no Man, I think denies.</note>Indeed the Caſe of <hi>David,</hi> and ours, agree not in any one Circumſtance. If <hi>David</hi>'s Example be imitable by us; then, as all Men I think will confeſs, that it was lawful for him to take Arms to Head a Party to defend himſelf: Then is it not lawful by this Example for the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> to take Arms? and if ſo, then how can any Man be bound not to take Arms againſt the King upon any Pretence whatſoever by virtue of a Law, when it is lawful by the Example of <hi>David,</hi> to take up Arms? But you will ſay, That <hi>David</hi> fled and ſhifted for Himſelf. Yea, true, But whither can the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> (I mean the Proteſtant Subjects, which being the Majority of the Kingdom, may be called <hi>the Kingdom</hi>) flee? Where could we have Caves or Gariſons to ſhift our Wives and Children into? Yea, more, Our King fled, and was not purſued by the Sword; he was in the Power of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and was neither depoſed nor killed, nor as much as the Lap of his Garment cut off, nor threatned if he would not go. Who of all the great Men in Arms did as much as ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, as the followers of <hi>David</hi> did? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.4. Had the King pleaſed to return to his place of Governing by Law, and ſufficient Caution and Security given ſo to do, he might have ſtaid at <hi>White-hall</hi> in Peace and Honour: but that would not be, and God hath done above all we would ask or think.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But here was a Reſiſtance, and that is determined to be ſinful, and damnable, by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2. <hi>Whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I conceive the Apoſtle doth not, by God's appointment, inſtitute any Form of Government in that place, neither Imperial, nor Monarchical; much leſs doth he ſpeak of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, unlimited Kings.<note place="margin">And the <hi>Nero</hi> was an Alſolute Twa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſile ſpeaks only of Authority, or lawful limited Power.</note> But there is an admirable perfect Draught of Government and Magiſtracy. The Magiſtrate is a Perſon clothed with Authority, armed with the Sword, with Power and juſt Force to defend the Good, to puniſh the Evil-doers: And ſo he is the Miniſter of God to thee
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:94791:25"/>for Good. There is a diſtinction between Good and Evil under him; that which is Good, is preſcribed by good Laws; that which is Evil is forbidden by Law. A good Magiſtrate, that is the Miniſter of God, doth govern by Law, and looks to the righteous adminiſtration of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to juſt Laws. The Sword is the Sword of Peace and Juſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, as well as of War in a juſt Cauſe; the End of this Ordinance of God, is publick Good. I ask you, Doctor, is Popery an Ordinance of God? I the introduction of Popery, and holding correſpondence with the Pope, by an Embaſſador, and a Nuncio, an Ordinance of God? Is Arbitrary Power an Ordinance of God? When you prove theſe to be Divine Ordinances, then lift up your Voice like a Trumpet and declame againſt Rebellion; for theſe were ſome of the Things oppoſed and reſiſted by our Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, with their Forces. Could the King lawfully become the Miniſter of the Pope, and Jeſuits, for Evil to the Nation? Had he Law and Right upon his ſide to do what he did, and what he was carrying on almoſt to a Concluſion? Was he not bound to govern by Law, and to keep his Word?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>What or all theſe Queſtions? What do you mean?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhall have more Queſtions yet. What Authority had the late King to change the Government in the Eſſential parts of it? Had he the Legiſlative Power in Himſelf? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no. Then where the Legiſlative is, there the Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is.<note place="margin">The Supreme Power is in the Legiſlative.</note> And the Supreme Governour hath his Authority to rule according to thoſe Laws enacted by the Legiſlators by way of truſt. The Prerogative and Power of the King, is often acknowledged by K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, to be in him by <hi>way of Truſt.</hi> in his Anſw. to the <hi>xix. Propoſ.</hi> p. 1. p. 5. <hi>lin. ult.</hi> p. 18. <hi>The Government, according to theſe Laws, is truſted to the King,</hi> p. 23. A truſt by God, Nature, and the Laws: true in ſeveral reſpects. He who acted without, beſide, and contrary to the Law, not only touching private particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſon, and Cauſes, but Root and Branch of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, was the King that was reſiſted in <hi>England,</hi> and no other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But he is truſted by God, and Nature, as well as by the Laws; ſuppoſe he broke his Truſt according to Laws he is not deprived of his Truſt according to God and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:94791:26"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Power of the King is a Truſt.</note>I anſwer: The truſt received from God and Nature, is, to govern righteouſly, and no otherwiſe, is it not? if it be, then he is truſted by God and Nature to govern according to the righteous Laws of the Kingdom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But we ought to have ſuffered to the uttermoſt, and not have reſiſted our lawful King, the Lord's Anointed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p n="1">1. We deny, that we reſiſted a Lawful King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They who preach'd up Paſſive Obedience, ſeemed to preach altogether in deſign upon others. Had we ſeen them lead more mortified Lives, had they denied themſelves more, we might have believed they were in earneſt. But who drank Claret more freely? lived more delicately? or were more covetous, if not ravenous for Preferment after, and upon Preferment for themſelves and their Friends, than the moſt of them?</p>
               <p n="3">3. I have not ſeen the Ceremonies of the Coronation, I heard and believe he was Crown'd, but heard not he was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed; but if he was Annointed, there is an <hi>Ordinatio Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionis, &amp; Ordinatio Commiſſionis,</hi> as the Reverend Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> diſtinguiſheth, in his Sermon on <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. Before K. <hi>Charles</hi> I. at <hi>York,</hi> May 15. 1639. apply it. And it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that God, who permitted a Popiſh King to rule a while, he did not permit him long; but when it was to be determined, whether he ſhould go on in his Ways, God took away his Spirit, that he could not command the Sword, in which he truſted. There was no more done againſt him, than what <hi>David</hi> did, nor ſo much; and God moſt graciouſly interpoſed, and ſuffered no more to be done. And ſo the Great God, the Fountain and Giver of Authority, hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined the Caſe. And there are two Notifications of his Will made known,
<list>
                     <item>1. In taking away Counſel and Power from the One; and,</item>
                     <item>2. raiſing a mighty Spirit of Courage and Conduct, in the often deſpiſed Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and that State, and turning the Spirits of this great People like one Man, to oppoſe Popery and Slavery.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But Providence is dark, and an uncertain Guide; look to the Rule, the Law of God and Man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Such apparent Providences are to be adored, as Supreme Deciſions, of Caſes reſerved in the Divine Power.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:94791:26"/>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Is not writing againſt the King's Will, Reſiſtance?</note>2. I ask, by what Law did ſo many Learned Men oppoſe Popery, and the King's Will, with their Learned Pens? Had they Law for it? ſhew it. Was not that a Reſſiſtance? and a provoking one too? For ought I know, by the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, a Souldier may take his Sword, who cannot diſpute and write in this Cauſe, as juſtly as a Scholar or a Divine may take his Pen and oppoſe. I grant a Diſparity in the Inſtrument and way of Reſiſtance, but the Reaſon or Motives of the one and the other the ſame. But as the one doth it to maintain the Truth of God, to confute Idolatry and Errors, and to ſave Souls; ſo doth the other, and more than the Scholar doth, for he labours to ſave Life and Eſtate, Liberty and Property, and the Proteſtant Religion abroad, from being perſecuted out of the World, whereas the Scholar by his Diſputes doth irritate, and defends the Cauſe, but not the Perſons that are in danger. And why may not a Peer of <hi>England,</hi> and a Gentleman, uſe all his Power, Wiſdom, and Intereſt in ſuch a Caſe, as well as a Scholar uſe his Reaſon and his Books? The Diſputant is not paſſive, but doth reſiſt in his way; and is it not then unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to contradict, as well in its kind, as to contra-act.</p>
               <p>Is it lawful for me to defend my Inheritance by Law, from the King's Incroachment? You'l ſay, it is. And why is it not lawful for a Kingdom to defend their Inheritance in Religion, and Laws, by the Sword, when there is no other way left? There's a Treaſon againſt a Government, as well as againſt a Governor. Every free-Man of <hi>England</hi> hath a ſhare in the benefit of the Fundamental Conſtitution, and ought to be aid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and aſſiſting in his place to defend it, from pernicious Changes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But is it fit the people ſhould judg?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>That kind of Paſſive-Obedience, ill ſtated, and ill timed alſo, is blind Obedience. The Wiſe, and Great, and Good Men of the Kingdom, are competent Judges of Fact, and Law alſo. And a ſhare is due to them in the Legiſlative alſo, and a ſhare is due to them in the Judicial and Executive Power. And if they clearly ſee through right Mediums, that they are in danger of being denied their Right, I ask you, What Law doth forbid them to vindicate their Right, and defend the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? There is no Law of <hi>England</hi> that doth forbid the Kingdom to preſerve its Legiſlative Power, and Hereditary
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:94791:27"/>Right, to a great ſhare in the Government. And their lying ſtill in ſuch a Caſe as ours, had been to ſuffer the ruin of the Ancient Eſtabliſhment, and the erection of a New, after a Jeſuital Model. There is no poſitive Law that forbids all En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, even by Force againſt Force in Extremity, when Right cannot be had without it; and if the King be but one of the three Eſtates of the Kingdom, (as K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt ſeems to me clearly to aſſert, <hi>Anſw. to the XIX Propoſ.</hi> p. 12, 13, 18, 19, 21. of the firſt Edit. making himſelf One, and the Houſes of Lords and Commons the other Two; and not as ſome others, who make the Temporal Lords one, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual the other, and the Commons the third); Then the Lords and Commons have two parts in the Legiſlation and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and if they have not a ſuppoſed Right, (which <hi>they never gave up, nor was ever taken from them, nor parted with</hi>) to preſerve and vindicate their Rights and Liberties, and that by Force, or forcible Attempts, when other ways have been uſed to no purpoſe; and when Arbitrary Power ſtrikes at the Root of the Conſtitution; then if they have no inherent Right to maintain their Right to their Liberties and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they have no right to the things themſelves, but owe them altogether to the meer Grace, and hold them at the meer Will of the King: if ſo, then he is an Abſolute Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, and may at pleaſure make us abſolute paſſive Slaves. But the Monarchy of <hi>England</hi> is a regulated limited Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, we have a legal Right to our Liberties, Properties, and Religion; and the Lords and Commons never parted with their Fundamental Rights, therefore they may vindicate them by their Power and Force, in Extremity and apparent Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But the Primitive Chriſtians did not reſiſt Tyrants and Perſecutors, though they had Force and Armies; as <hi>Tertullian</hi> and others declare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>The Caſe of the Primitive Chriſtians in nothing to Ours. Chriſtians as Chriſtians have no Weapons but Chriſtian, no more than Subjects as Subjects have a right to Arms, and to make Reſiſtance. And they were then in the ſtate of meer Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. Had they a right of Election to be Senators? Had they a legal eſtabliſhment of their Religion? Was their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent demanded by Heralds, to have ſuch a Man for their
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:94791:27"/>Emperor? Did the Emperor ſwear at his Inauguration, to govern by Laws, in the making of which they had a ſhare? Dr. <hi>Falkener</hi> arguing againſt Subjects taking Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, ſhews, we need not fear to be driven to it, for we have the ſecurity of good and wholſom Laws, fixed with us by general accord of King, Lords, and Commons— And it is a great Priviledg in this Realm, that both Civil Rights, and Matters of Religion, are eſtabliſhed by our Laws; and that no Law can be made or repealed, nor publick Monies rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but by the Conſent of the Commons, <hi>&amp;c. B.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 378. Had the Condition of the Primitive Chriſtians been like ours, we have no reaſon to think, but they would have vindicated their own Right; as, had our Condition been the ſame with theirs, I hope, through Grace, we ſhould have put on the Crown of ☜ Martyrdom as they did. The Queſtion is not, Whether it be lawful for Subjects to take Arms againſt their King, when they have their Rights and Religion eſtabliſhed by Laws, and thoſe preſerved; but whether a Kingdom, the Peers, Gentry, and Body of it, may not vindicate their Legal Rights, both Sacred and Civil, by open Force, in conjunction with a free Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Prince, who hath a Right in the Kingdom to preſerve, when there is an apparent Neceſſity, either ſo to do, or ſuffer and intollerable kind of Government to come upon them?<note place="margin">Our Caſe put home.</note> And that, at ſuch a time when their Paſſive Stupidity, Dulneſs, Compliance, or Cowardiſe, would ruin their Poſterity, and extreamly hazard every Proteſtant State and Kingdom to a ſpeedy ruin and deſolation, whom we ought to our power to preſerve.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath been always Loyal, and the Friends of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>And may they be ſo now, to our moſt wiſe and gracious King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> I do not very well know, Doctor, what Church of <hi>England</hi> you mean; for there have been ſeveral Alterations in it ſince reformed; nor who you take to be the Friends of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> If you mean ſuch as the Convocation was 1640, as Dr. <hi>Falkener</hi> ſeems to mean, <hi>B.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 338. or the Compilers of the <hi>Homilies,</hi> and their Friends, as he alſo ſeems to mean, wit the Judgment of the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> (ſuppoſed to be written by Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon</hi>) then all theſe Friends will not well agree together.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:94791:28"/>
               <p>I do take a great number of the Clergy in 1640, to be of the new faſhion'd Church that ſome had been long a making, an were near to finiſh. Others were true Friends to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, as at firſt old-faſhion'd true Friends to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Purity and Peace upon equal Terms. Give me leave to preſent to you, good Doctor, ſome of their Sentiments. And I ſhall ſhew you what the Old Friends of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> of the firſt Edition, have ſaid to theſe Matters in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate between us. And, firſt, many of your Acquaintance, Doctor, have ſpit in the Face of the Churches of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, and ſlandered them as polluted with rebellious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Practices. But the old true Friends of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have wip'd off the Spittle, and clear'd them from it. They have acknowledged the Form of Government to be divers in divers Countries; they have vindicated the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k Doctrine of the Reformed Paſtors, and candidly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted the Reſiſtances made againſt their Tyrannical Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and allowed Reſiſtance, by force of Arms, of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, in ſome Caſes. I fear I ſhould be too tedious in giving you Quotations at large, I ſhall only refer you to the Writings of the undoubted Friends of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Great Aſſiſtances were ſent from <hi>England,</hi> by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to preſerve the States of the <hi>Low Countries.</hi> Sir <hi>John Forteſcue,</hi> in his Speech in Parliament, <hi>Anno</hi> 35 of the Queen, ſaid, <q>As for the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> they ſtood her Majeſty, yearly, ſince ſhe undertook <hi>the Defence of them,</hi> in one hundred and fifty thouſand Pounds. The Burden of four Kingdoms hath reſted upon her Majeſty.</q>
Sir <hi>Simon Dew</hi>'s Journal of the Parliaments in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign. And how commonly are thoſe Provinces termed <hi>Rebels</hi> againſt the King of <hi>Spain?</hi> King <hi>James</hi> calls thoſe that revolted from the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and that were forced to make Reſiſtance for Religion in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Saints of God; Et nonnè jam Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mota ſunt ubi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> arma</hi> &amp; in Sactos, <hi>qui per Galliam &amp; per Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium ſunt directa? Commentatio de Antichriſto,</hi> printed after Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Abbot</hi>'s <hi>B. Demonſtratio Antichriſti,</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. p. 477. That Learned King had not Sainted them, if he had thought them Rebels. See Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi>'s <hi>Defence of the Apology,</hi> p. 16, 17. And what a great Friend was he to the Church of <hi>England?</hi> See famous Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi>'s (another particular Friend of Hers)
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:94791:28"/>
                  <hi>True Difference,</hi> Edit. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>p.</hi> 512, 515, 518, 519, 520, 521. Biſhop <hi>Robert Abbot,</hi> who wrote a Learned Book, <hi>De Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ Regiâ Majeſtate;</hi> and the more to be noted for that, was <hi>Regius</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity in <hi>Oxford,</hi> hath a notable Paſſage, <hi>Demonſtratio Antichriſti,</hi> p. 150, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> c. 7. §. 6. Biſhop <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s <hi>Treatiſe of Satisfaction,</hi> hath one part called, <hi>A Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Proteſtants in Caſe of Rebellion.</hi> There are no Seditious Paſſages in any of theſe Reverend Authors. But if theſe were not in them, what would they be call'd in others? I note this out of <hi>Jewel;</hi> neither doth any of theſe (meaning <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Melancthon</hi>) teach their People to rebel againſt their Princes, but only to defend themſelves againſt Oppreſſion, by all lawful means, as did <hi>David</hi> againſt <hi>Saul.</hi> So do the Nobles in <hi>France</hi> at this day. Then to take Arms is a lawful Means, by conſequence, (for <hi>David</hi> took Arms, and the Nobles in <hi>France</hi>) —They themſelves are beſt acquainted with the Laws and Conſtitutions of their Country, <hi>p.</hi> 16. Touching the Queen of <hi>Scotland,</hi> I will ſay nothing. The Kingdoms and States of the World have ſundry <hi>Agreements</hi> and Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. The Nobles and Commons there, neither drew the Sword, nor attempted Force againſt the Prince. They ſought only the continuance of God's undoubted Truth, and defence of their own Lives, againſt your barbarous and cruel Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>p.</hi> 17. See Addition out of Biſhop <hi>Bilſon.</hi> I obſerve, he vindicates <hi>Beza,</hi> and the Proteſtant Divines, and to our Caſe of late in <hi>England</hi> may be applied. That which may be done by the Laws of Kingdoms and States, is lawful, and not rebellious, as in the Civil Wars of <hi>France,</hi> p. 511. The Princes in <hi>Germany</hi> may lawfully reſiſt the Emperor, and by Force reduce him to the Ancient and received Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or elſe repel him as a Tyrant, and ſet another in his place, by the Right and Freedom of their Country, <hi>p.</hi> 513. We grant it to be true, that if the Laws of the Land, as in ſome places they do, warrant to depoſe their Governor, <hi>p.</hi> 517. He quotes the Judgment of <hi>Luther,</hi> when he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by Lawyers, that the States of <hi>Germany</hi> might defend themſelves againſt the Emperor, and diſplace him, <hi>p.</hi> 518. <hi>If a Prince ſhould go about to ſubject his Kingdom to a Foreign</hi> ☜ <hi>Realm, or change the Form of the Common-Wealth, from Empery to Tyranny; or neglect the Laws eſtabliſhed by Common Conſent of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:94791:29"/>Prince and People, to execute his own Pleaſure: In theſe and other Caſes which might be named, if the Nobles and Commons join to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to defend their ancient and accuſtomed Liberty, they may not well be accounted Rebels,</hi> p. 520. <hi>In Kingdoms where Princes bear Rule by the Sword, we do not mean the Prince's private Will againſt his Laws, but his Precept derived from his Laws,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ibid.</hi> He excuſeth the <hi>Germans,</hi> and <hi>Flemings;</hi> and of the <hi>Scots</hi> he <note place="margin">☞</note> ſpeaks full to our Caſe. <hi>The</hi> Scots, <hi>what have they done beſides the placing the Right Heir, and her own Son, when the Mother fled and forſook the Realm? Be theſe thoſe furious Attempts and Rebellions you talk of?</hi> I grant, he ſaith, our Princes are Hereditary, and that Subjects are abſolutely bound to obey, <hi>p.</hi> 515, 517. But if we are abſolutely bound to obey, then the King of <hi>England</hi> is an Abſolute Prince, which he is not over, or in reſpect of his Subjects, becauſe he rules by Laws made by their Conſent, though he be abſolute in reſpect. of any Foreign State.</p>
               <p>The Paſſage quoted in Biſhop <hi>Rob. Abbot</hi> is notable through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. I'll onely cull out of it. <hi>Hic vero politica res agitur, Quid Principi juris in Subditos per Leges cujuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Reip. fundatrices promiſſum ſit.</hi> 
                  <q>What Power is promiſed to the Prince over Subject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, by the Fundamental Laws of every Common-wealth; whether he have (<hi>infinitam</hi>) a boundleſs, unlimit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Power, or a moderate, temperate, more or leſs, by the arbitrament of the Nobles or People. The Roman Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror was Arbitrary, and Abſolute; had Power of Life and Death. Wherefore the Chriſtians could with no Pretence, or Colour, reſtrain the Violence of thoſe Times, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit thoſe Injuries by which they were vexed. But the Princes of thoſe Nations, which thou (<hi>Bellarmine</hi>) doſt mention, have certain Bounds ſet them, which when they exceed, the Nobles think it is lawful for them to repel un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Force, and ſhake off the Yoke by which they are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, contrary to Right and Law.</q>
And then defends the Cauſe of the Proteſtants in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>France.</hi> 
                  <q>And in this there is a difference between theſe Churches, and the Primitive, which was ſubject to the meer pleaſure of the Emperor, without the leaſt Title to any Law of their own. But when they were armed with publick Right under <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> they were not only kill'd, as before, but did kill,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:94791:29"/>and having overcome <hi>Licinius,</hi> and the Tyrants, they eaſed their Necks of the Yoke of Perſecution. And in ſuch a way, or for a like reaſon, hath our Church done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                     <bibl>p. 152.</bibl>
                  </q>
— I know there is another ſort of Friends to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but I think theſe now named as worthy of the Name as they, and more to the Honour of it. And theſe ſhall ſuffice. I do forbear to turn to Foreign Divines, that have been in reputation in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe I will not be further troubleſome to you.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Judicium <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitatis Oxonienſis,</hi> It goes upon thoſe Suppoſitions, and handles thoſe Matters, which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lien to our preſent Caſe, and therefore I forbear looking into it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But that which ſticks with me, is my Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Why did you not aſſiſt the Perſon of the King to the utmoſt of your Power, to drive out the Invader, and to ruin your Church and Kingdom? Why did you oppoſe him in his Declaration of Indulgence? But I ſpare you. Only a few Queſtions more and adone. It is plain, the King did voluntarily put himſelf out of the Exerciſe of his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Poſſeſſion of his Kingdoms. Is it to be thought that the Kingdom would be without a King, during his pleaſure? or did he not really think, that in the Vacancy, the Kingdom would chooſe another? If he thought they would fill the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy, then why did he give way to it? If you ſay, there was a Neceſſity for him to depart, in point of Honour and Safety. I know not what his Reaſons were; but be they never ſo many, or great, in his Opinion, I go upon Matter of Fact. The Throne being voided by his own Act, muſt it not be filled? and did he not think, and foreſee it would? then, why did he not prevent it? why did he give way to it? If he made way for a Succeſſor,<note place="margin">Allegiance is not enjoined during the King's na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Life.</note> he made himſelf <hi>a Dead King in his natural Life-time;</hi> and Allegiance is due to him no longer than he is King. Suppoſe he ſhould put himſelf into a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, or Colledge of Jeſuites, or go to <hi>Rome,</hi> or in Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and put Himſelf out of capacity to govern the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, doth the Bond of a my Allegiance hold, and continue in force upon me? He is a uncapable of ruling us in <hi>France,</hi> as in any of thoſe places; therefore I ſee no reaſon but to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:94791:30"/>conclude, my Bond of Allegiance is cancell'd and diſſolved.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But! two Kings at a time in being? What! two Suns in One Firmament?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I know but one King, and one Queen, both joined in the ſame Regality. Your Sun is ſet, he put out his own Light. Be not ſo fond of your late King, as if you had loſt your Miſtreſs, and were reſolved never to have another; for you muſt have another King, and Queen too, as it happens, we have, by the wonderful Providence and Gift of God, to theſe Kingdoms, ſince you and I began our diſcourſe. Come, Sir, let me play a little upon you, I will not hurt you. Were you ſo truly and perfectly Loyal to K. <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> as not to wiſh for <hi>James,</hi> while you look'd upon Him as the Riſing Sun, that was to Crown your Ambition with Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Happy Days? K. <hi>Charles</hi> went out with little Mourning, and <hi>James,</hi> came up with greateſt Admiration. You were like Perſian Idolaters at his Aſcent. Do not mourn too much at his Ecclipſe? It was his own Free-will; and we had no reaſon to reſiſt his Will in going away, and thereby making room for ſuch a Succeſſion, as is to the hearty Joy of the ſerious part of the Nation, and the univerſal Joy of all Proteſtants in <hi>Europe!</hi> Four Years ago, a gloomy Look, was by <hi>innuendo</hi> a ſign of a diſloyal Heart; there was a great deal of diſſembled cheerfulneſ. I hope, Doctor, you will never be preſented nor troubled for a diſcontented Look, nor indicted for a little fit of Sulleneſs. Come, Doctor, ſatisfy your ſelf with St. <hi>Paul's</hi> wholeſome Doctrine; <hi>The Powers that be, are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God,</hi> (I believe more than thoſe you hanker after) and hear what a Great Friend of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Advocate for her Ceremonies, I mean, the truly worthy Admirer of Free-Grace, and <hi>Calvin's</hi> Friend, the old Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> of <hi>Dureſm</hi> ſpeaks; <q>Are they then Once eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? then whatſoever the Government be, they are of God, God owneth them, they may not be diſturbed. For as Silver, whilſt it is meer Plate, if it be tendred for Exchange, may be either taken, or not, by the Party to whom it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered: but if it once receive the King's Stamp, and be coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it is Currant Mony, and may not be refuſed; Or as Acts of Parliament, whilſt they are but voted, are but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Conſents, but after they have the King's Royal Aſſent,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:94791:30"/>they become Statutes, which may not be tranſgreſſed. So it is in Governments; as ſoon as it is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated by Man (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> calleth it) becometh (thus St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, God's Ordinance,<note place="margin">Ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. at <hi>York</hi> before the King, <hi>1639</hi>
                     </note> and may not be reſiſted.</q>
Now, Sir, Our Choſen King and Queen are Created by Man, a Convention that had greater Power and Truſt committed to them, than any Parliament before them ſince this Government was firſt moulded,<note place="margin">The late Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Authority than any ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Parliament.</note> and are the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, therefore ſcatter the clouds and look up. Receive them as from God, and be ſubject for the Lord's ſake and their own: And to move you from a weighty motive, the preſent World; Had your King been let alone a while, and you ſo honeſt as to refuſe to read his Declaration, you had been a Doctor, without Preferment; and therefore, come the worſt that can come by a Comprehenſion, you may have at leaſt one Living; and if you muſt preach twice, you will have, I hope, peace, to ſtudy to make two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, or otherwiſe to edify the Souls of Men in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon as well as the Morning.</p>
               <p>And now, Doctor, I come to the end of what, at our firſt meeting we fell upon: As I intended, by the help of God, to obſerve the <hi>Thanksgiving, Febr.</hi> 14. ſo I have. And can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Expreſs the Senſe I have of the many Cauſes of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving. <hi>Behold and wonder at what God hath wrought! Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on belongeth unto the Lord, his Bleſſing is upon his People! The Lord hath anſwered before we called,</hi> Iſa. 65.24. <hi>Who hath heard ſuch a thing? who hath ſeen ſuch a thing? Shall the Earth be made to bring forth in one day? or ſhall a Nation be born at Once? for as ſoon as</hi> Zion <hi>travelled, ſhe brought forth Children.</hi> Iſa. 66.8. There are three admirable Providences, to be told our Children, that the Generations to come may praiſe the Lord.
<list>
                     <item>1. The Greatneſs of our Deliverance, from the Sins, the Curſe, the Plague of Popery; the deliverance of our Bodies from the Sword, of our Wives and Virgins from unnatural beaſtlineſs, of Papiſts who put Nature to ſhame,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>As in</hi> Savoy, 1686.</note> and yet their Nature cannot bluſh.</item>
                     <item>2. The Deliverance without Blood.</item>
                     <item>3. The Suddaineſs of it. Providence diſpatched his marvellous Work.</item>
                     <item>4. The immediateneſs of God's hand.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. After a Deliverance, we are come to a Settlement, the moſt hopeful this Nation ever ſaw; in many reſpects it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:94791:31"/>all that ever went before it; as the Deliverance alſo doth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That God ſhould make way for it, by taking away the Spirit of the late King, and coveying him away, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to our Religion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Lord wonderfully united the Spirit of the Nation in the choice of Repreſentatives; and united their Counſels, without tedious diſtracting Debates, to fill the Throne, to clear and recover their own deſpiſed, and almoſt extinguiſhed Rights, and to do Right to our moſt Gracious King and Queen, and the Royal Line, upon better terms than they were in before.</p>
               <p n="5">5. God hath given a King and Queen of our own Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that the true, rarely ſet off with an iluſtrious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarineſs, Zeal, and Moderation.</p>
               <p n="6">6. I rejoice for the joy of the perſecuted, deſolated Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches abroad; and ſtrength added to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Princes.</p>
               <p n="7">7. I rejoice for the Conſolation which this wonderful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence hath brought to Proteſtants abroad that have ſuffered Perſecution, and that were in danger to be ſwallowed up: and that the Proſperity and Peace of <hi>England,</hi> is like to add Courage and Strength to Proteſtant Princes and States every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
               <p n="8">8. I rejoice that Popery is put to ſhame and confuſion in our Land. I wiſh the Simple and Deluded may ſee the Hand of God which is lifted up, and not love Darkneſs rather than Light. The Lord hath broken the Head of Popiſh Counſels, diſcloſed their Secrets, and made them fall in their own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices.</p>
               <p n="9">9. I hope the Lord will finiſh his work, and having brought to the Birth, will alſo bring forth, <hi>Shall I cauſe to bring forth, and ſhut the Womb? ſaith the Lord.</hi> Iſa. 66.9.</p>
               <p n="10">10. I hope to ſee Proteſtants united more in the profeſſion of Faith, Love, Worſhip, Communion, and Peace, that there be no Colour from Laws to ſcatter the Flocks; put Lights under Buſhels, and make them a Prey to the worſt of Men.</p>
               <p n="11">11. I hope to ſee with admiration, <hi>Behold! a King ſhall reign in Righteouſneſs, and Princes ſhall rule in Judgment;—
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:94791:31"/>that the Work of Righteouſneſs ſhall be Peace, and the Effect of Righteouſneſs, Quietneſs, and Aſſurance for ever.</hi> Iſa. 32.1, 17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. I hope Our gracious King, Queen, and wiſe Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who are taking off Arbitrary Yokes apace, will take off another Yoke of Arbitrarineſs in Eccleſiaſtical Courts. I do not winch becauſe I am gall'd; but rejoice becauſe I am delivered and preſerved. There is a great ſenſe among us of the Arbitrarineſs of Canonical Obedience, which was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended even to Votes for Parliament-Men, and anſwering Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, as in the High Commiſſion, proceeding upon Arbitrary Canons, not confirmed by the King's Proclamation; Arbitrary Articles of Viſitation, Arbitrary Oaths exacted of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens, and their Legal Duties never that I could hear of explained unto them: And calling for Subſcriptions to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes and Abhorrences, to ſerve the Deſigns of Papiſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and deceive the King with Promiſes.</p>
               <p n="13">13. I rejoice, that I am in my place to ſerve God, out of which I was preparing my ſelf to be thrown out, for not reading the King's Declaration (as it was a means to advance Popery, and not out of a grudg at the Indulgence of Proteſtants) which had been the means of our ruin, if God had not given him an unexpected Diverſion, to look to his own Kingdom, and found him other Work.</p>
               <p>Every day will I praiſe the Lord, and call upon mine own Soul to bleſs the Lord, and not to forget all his Benefits; and I will, by the Grace of God, ſtir up others, with an, <hi>O that Men would praiſe the Lord!</hi> &amp;c. And as I have, ſince I was capable, kept the 5th of <hi>November,</hi> ſo now, while I can, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another Reaſon, the moſt ſeaſonable peaceable, happy entrance of our now more Illuſtrious, that the then Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> as a Day which the Lord hath made. My Joys may be grievous to you, which I am ſorry for; and therefore I will pray, that we may not fail as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did, to return thanks according to the Mercy received. There are thouſands and ten thouſands of Mercies and Bleſſings in this marvellous Deliverance and Settlement of the Kingdom; nothing can blaſt this hopeful Spring, and ſilence the ſinging of Birds, but our continuance in Prodigious Profaneneſs and Debauchery, brought in at the very Heels of the joyful Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:94791:32"/>of the <hi>King</hi> in 1660. If the ſenſe of Mercy doth but run through our Hearts, and oblige us to think as well of the Practice of Religion, (as it is deſcribed, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13. and other places) as we think ill of Popery, all your new <hi>Sect of Grumblers</hi> can only give us ſome exerciſe of our Charity and Moderation; you, and all your Party, under your anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quated, and ſelf-depoſed King, with the hopeful ſucceſſion of the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and his Brother in the <hi>little</hi> Belly of the Queen, cannot hurt us. Therefore, Good Doctor, <hi>grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> not againſt God, our Laws, our King, and Queen, and Parliament, the hoped-for ſettlement of the Church upon the Word of God, maintained by <hi>unity of Spirit in the Bond of Peace,</hi> and commended in a Better Act, than our laſt of Uniformity, or elſe we ſhall go as far back, as that Act caſt the happineſs of this Church and Kingdom. For from that day that Act took place, it hath been ill with the Church of God, and Chriſtianity in <hi>England,</hi> and a private Apartment was made for Popery, under the Church Walls.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>Are you a Conformiſt, and ſay ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>You have called us <hi>Trimmers;</hi> and our Conformity hath been in a great part from the Principle of Paſſive Obedience, and Peace and Love to Souls, reſolving to go as far with you as we could with a good Conſcience. And ſince our Eyes have been opened to ſee the tendency of Affairs, we can think no leſs, and have good Authority for what we ſay. Godlineſs and Honeſty, with Quietneſs and Peace, is the deſire of our Souls. And, Doctor, do not Grumble: Let not your Eye be Evil, becauſe God is Good. What! hate Popery, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the King's Declaration, and now hanker after your King, whom you cannot have without Popery, if he were not ſhut out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>Conſcience and Allegiance.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>It is well the power of Conſcience is at leaſt acknowledged. Conſcience was Fanaticiſm a great while, and a religious Pretence for Rebellion, and the worſt of Actions. I wiſh you a well-ſetled, enlightned Conſcience. And for your Allegiance pay it where it is now due, by God's Providence to a Wonder; by the Laws of the Land, we have God, the Laws, King, Queen, and Parliament for us. Come down, down Doctor, ſoft and fair, there are a pair of Stairs from your coming down from
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:94791:32"/>you Pinacles, who had never got up, had you not been better at flying up, than orderly Motions and leiſurely Aſcents. Take your ſhare of a happy Peace, and be glad you are not forced by an Act of Parliament, to renounce your Allegiance to your deceaſed King, as the <hi>Non-Cons</hi> were to renounce the Covenant. Preach Peace, and perſwade the Gentlemen of the Swear, and the Sword, to be thankful they came off ſo well, and were not kill'd and damn'd at on Day, according to their Atheiſtical Wiſhes, for God was againſt them; the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> was Ordained of God to be Victor, and now King. But, Sir, I perceive your Colour comes, I will therefore diſmiſs you calmly, Live in Peace and Love; Do the Work and Will of God, and ſo farewel. The God of Peace go with you.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="after-debate">
            <head>
               <hi>An After-Debate,</hi> Of the Original Contract. <hi>P. W.</hi> Convention: And no Allegiance due to the late King.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>I Am come again to viſit you, and to ſhew you ſomething that's worth your reading and conſideration too. There are ſome things for you to chew upon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>You are very welcome to me at all times, who deſire a fairneſs and friendſhip with you; and if there be a ſcuffle of Notions, let us labour to prevent the drawing of Blood, and bringing in Popery and Miſery about our Ears. There are a new Sect of Seminaries ſculking and haunting up and down, ſowing their Diſcontents and ill Nature, under the Name of <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Religion;</hi> but the beſt is, their Notions are like heated Corn, chitted in their Brains, that I hope they will not grow, nor come up ſo tall, as to hide a Rebel in. Well, but, Sir, what have you to ſhew me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>Here's and ingenious Paper, called, <hi>The Deſertion Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs'd,</hi> in a Letter to a Country Gentleman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I will peruſe it, and deal with it as I find it, or as I am
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:94791:33"/>able. And though you think me prepoſſeſt, yet I am as willing to ſind out Truth, as any of you can be. Let us read him to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and be pleaſed to inſiſt upon what you think moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial in him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>I think it is all material, and well penn'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>If it be ſo material, I were beſt leave him to be handled by the Author of the <hi>Enquiry into the Preſent State of Affairs,</hi> whom he takes into his hands to diſcuſs. And if the Bones of his Subject will bear Diſcuſſion, without breaking or disjoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he will ſleep the better in a bad Lodging. If any thing be left out by me, think not the Paper unanſwerable, for I do not intend a Diſcuſſion of him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. How ſaith the Gentleman to him? <hi>Can the Seat of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be empty, while the King, who all grant, had an unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable Title, is ſtill living, and his Abſence forced and involun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary?</hi> Here are Suppoſitions imply'd, that ſhould firſt be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: As,
<list>
                     <item>1. A King once ſuppoſed to have a good Title, muſt needs have it during Life.</item>
                     <item>2. That during a King's na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Life, the Throne cannot be empty.</item>
                     <item>3. Tho it is true, in a ſenſe, that the King's Abſence be Involuntary; ſo in a ſenſe it was Voluntary.</item>
                  </list>
It was a mixt Action, and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for his leaving the Kingdom are not altogether unknown; and whatever the Neceſſity was, his Counſellors, and Friends the Papiſts, with his own Affection to that Intereſt (which God hath croſt for the preſent, and ſuch as you, acting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God, are active to reſtore) brought upon him.</p>
               <p>In Anſwer to the Gentleman's Queſtion drawn up by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he ſaith, <q>The Gentlemen of the Convention, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare a Vacancy in the Government, lay the main ſtreſs of their Opinion, upon his Majeſty's withdrawing himſelf: <hi>For now eſpecially ſince the Story of the French League, and the Buſineſs of the Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>are paſt over in ſilence,</hi> moſt Men believe, that the <hi>pretended Breach,</hi> of that which they call <hi>the Original Contract,</hi> was deſign'd for no more than a Popular Flouriſh.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I confeſs to you, Doctor, theſe Lines are very material; of each branch I'le crop a little.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Noblemen and Gentlemen of the Convention, who had the <hi>Perſonal Majeſty lodged</hi> in them in a high degree; and that as they were a Convention, entruſted to act for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:94791:33"/>of <hi>England,</hi> did, doubtleſs, lay a great ſtreſs for their Judgment upon that, which is more than the Opinion of the <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> as he calls them. But the foregoing Actions of the King, terminated in that firſt Act, had their ſhare in influencing. that Publick Reaſon ſo to judg.</p>
               <p n="2">"The Story of the French League is paſt in ſilence. No, Sir, that which you and your Fellow-Rockers of the ſoft-headed Diſciples, call a <hi>Story,</hi> is not paſt away in ſilence yet. A Story you'd make it, as if all this Action was begotten by a Story, or two or three Fictions. I ſhall not without Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority relate what I have heard of that Story. But I build my belief of a deſigned Miſchief upon Publick Evidence, and undeniable, by adding a little uſe of Reaſon to it. My Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence riſeth out of <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Letters: <q>
                     <bibl>Letter to Sir <hi>W. Throck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morton,</hi> Feb. 1. 74/5.</bibl> For you well know, that when the Duke (the late King <hi>James</hi>) come to be Maſter of our Affairs,<note place="margin">Joint Intereſt with <hi>France.</hi>
                     </note> the King of <hi>France</hi> will have reaſon to promiſe himſelf all things that he can deſire. For, according to the Mind of the Duke, the Intereſts of the King of <hi>England,</hi> the King of <hi>France,</hi> and his own, are ſo cloſe bound up together, that it is impoſſible to ſeparate them the one from the other, without Ruin to all three; but being joined, they muſt, notwithſtanding all oppoſition, become invincible.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Letter to <hi>Monſ. le Cheeſe;</hi>
                     </bibl> The King of <hi>France</hi> eſteemed his Intereſt, and the Intereſt of his R. H. to be the ſame, <hi>p.</hi> 110. and that if his Royal Highneſs would endeavour to diſſolve the Parliament, his Majeſty (King of <hi>France</hi>) would aſſiſt him with his Power and Purſe, to have ſuch a new One as would be for their purpoſe. His Royal Highneſs was convinced their Intereſts were both one. A ſecond Letter to <hi>Le Cheeſe:</hi> We have here a mighty Work upon our Hands, no leſs than the Converſion of the three Kingdoms, and by that perhaps the ſubduing of a Peſtilent Hereſy, which has domineer'd over a great part of the Northern World a long time; there were never ſuch hopes of Succeſs ſince the Death of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> as now in our days; when God hath given us a Prince, who is become (may I ſay, a Miracle) zealous of being the Author and Inſtrument of ſo glorious a Work, <bibl>
                        <hi>Collect. of Letters,</hi> p. 118.</bibl>
                  </q>
Now ordinary Reaſon will hence
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:94791:34"/>advance the probability of all kind of mutual Engagements between theſe two Princes, to promote the Catholick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, by Dragooning us, either to turn Papiſts, or turn out of the Land. Pray, Sir, can you diſprove the Story, as you call it, of the French League? either by detecting the Impoſture, or by demonſtrating the unreaſonableneſs of the thing. Or is it ſufficient, that their being both entirely devoted to the innocent and harmleſs Society of the Jeſuits, to unite them in the ſame Heavenly and Spiritual Intereſt and Deſigns, as would make ſuch a League incredible and unſuppoſable?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thè Story of the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> (whoſe Right to the Crown is ſo clear to ſome of your Seminaries, that it is as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain as an Article of Faith) is not laid aſleep, nor paſt away in ſilence. We have read the Obſervations made upon him, in the <hi>Memorial,</hi> and upon the Queen's Progreſs with him. We give credit to the Letter of Father <hi>Petre</hi> to <hi>La Cheſe.</hi> 
                  <q>As to the Queen's being with Child, that Great Concern goes on as well as we could with, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you will agree with me (moſt Reverend Father) that we have done a great thing, by introducing Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> to the Queen, (this Woman is totally devoted to our Society.</q>
A rare Midwife of a Plot, to dig a Baby out of a Meal-Tub): <q>The zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Catholicks lay already two to one, that it will be a Prince, (he muſt be a Prince, or as good never be with Child).</q> But that which is pretty indeed in the Reverend Father, is, <q>That the King's Secret Council think good to wait for the Queen's Delivery that they may ſee a Succeſſor, who may have need of the whole Protection of the moſt Chriſtian King, to ſupport him &amp; maintain his Rights.</q> Now what was to become of the King of <hi>England?</hi> Whither was he to be ſent after the Birth of this young Succeſſor? the Queſtion may be asked of the Friends of that little Prince? for was King <hi>James</hi> to live or not? If he was to live, notwithſtanding the having of a Prince to ſucceed him, then why was not he able to ſupport and protect his Succeſſor, and his Rights? Or, was the King of <hi>England</hi> to be diſabled from ſupporting his Succeſſor? The Princes of <hi>Wales</hi> were never wont to have Guardians and Protectors out of the Engliſh Dominions. But this Unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Prince, would need Protection from a Foreign Monarch, <hi>and his whole Protection.</hi> A skirt of his Protection was not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:94791:34"/>large enough, he muſt have the whole Campaign Cloke of his Protection to Cover him, and to ſupport Him, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Rights? Why ſo?—Well, it ſeems Father <hi>Petre</hi> was a Fortuneteller of the young friendleſs injured Prince, that he muſt be carried to <hi>France,</hi> when young and tender, and ſtand in need of the whole Protection of a Great King.—</p>
               <p n="4">4. You ſay, That which they call the Original Contract, was deſigned for no <hi>more than a Popular Flouriſh.</hi> Now, Doctor how doth this appear, that it was no more than a Popular Flouriſh? what a kindneſs was the King's withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Gentlemen of the Convention, and Men of their Sentiments? had it not been for that, they would have had no ſtreſs for their opinion of the Vacancy. For, the French League was but a Story, the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> was but a Story, which they cared not how ſoon was laid aſleep, or put to ſilence. And what they call an Original Contract, was but a popular Flouriſh. Now, Doctor, becauſe your Author is a Man that leads, becauſe he writes, and againſt a whole Convention alſo, I will make ſome further diſcovery of this Contract, which others of the ſame Genius make ſo light of. And here I will ſhew, what ſome of Eminency of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have written of it. Theſe Men will not allow the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> to be as much as a Contracted Matron; but a Proſtitute to Abſolute Arbitrary Power.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Original Contract be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and People of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note>I have noted before how Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon</hi> doth labour to manifeſt the Abſurdity, if not Impoſſibility of any Contract between King and People. But if the People had at any time any Power of Electing their King, it is rational enough to conceive, that they made Conditions and Terms, and would never have conſented to their Hurt and Injury. There are ſeveral ways of acquiring Soveraign Power. Dr. <hi>Fern,</hi> whoſe appearance was eminent againſt Defenſive Arms, doth yet acknowledg. <q>It is probable indeed that Kings at firſt were by <hi>choice Here, as Elſewhere.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>The Reſolving of Conſcience, <hi>p.</hi> 19.—</bibl> This I ſpeak not as if the Kings of this Land might rule as Conquerors: God forbid. The King is bound unto all thoſe Laws, Grants, and Priviledges, and that by Oath.—Whereas Our King is King, before he comes to the Coronation, which is ſooner or later at his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:94791:35"/>pleaſure,<note place="margin">Then it ſeems Security muſt be given to the People.</note> but always to be <hi>in due time, in regard of the ſecurity his People</hi> receive by his taking the Oath, and he again mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually from them, in which performance <hi>there is ſomething like a Covenant, all but Forfeiture.</hi> The King there promiſes, and binds himſelf by Oath to performance. Could they ſhew us in this Covenant ſuch an Agreement between the King and his People, that in caſe he will not diſcharge his Truſt, that it ſhall be lawful for the States of the Kingdom, by Arms, to reſiſt, and provide for the Safety thereof, it were ſomething, <bibl>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 21.</bibl>
                  </q>
Here is a Covenant and Contract, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Oath; which is enough to qualify the Spirits of them who deride or expoſe it. And though there be no For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture mentioned, it doth not follow none can be incurred. There is a mutual Benevolence, Hope, and Confidence, in the Marriage of the <hi>ſponſus Regni</hi> to the Kingdom; it doth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow, the Marriage-Bond cannot be violated. Suppoſe all that ſwear Fealty to the King do break Faith with him, do they not forfeit their Priviledges, and Honours? yet where is it expreſt in the Contract or Capitulation? A Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment founded upon Contract and Agreement, is not ſo ſtrange a thing in it ſelf as ſome Men make it to be, when there are many Learned Writers that affirm, there can be no juſt and righteous Government, but by Election and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and that without it Government could not ſubſiſt. And others hold, though Election and Conſent be not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to a juſt Government, they ſay it is to a ſtable and permanent Government. <hi>Arniſaeus Relectionis politicae,</hi> L. 2. c. 2. Sect. 6. And, <hi>de facto William</hi> the Firſt, (who did not found his Authority upon Conqueſt) after he had waſted <hi>Suſſex, Kent,</hi> and other Counties, until he came to <hi>Boarcham,</hi> where Arch-Biſhop <hi>Aldred,</hi> and <hi>Wulſtan</hi> of <hi>Worceſter, Clito, Edgar,</hi> the Earles <hi>Edwin</hi> and <hi>Morcar,</hi> and Noblemen out of <hi>London,</hi> with many others, came to Him, and giving Hoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, they yielded to Him, <hi>and ſwore Allegiance. Cum quibus et ipſe foedus pepigit.</hi> With whom, He himſelf made a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. <hi>Floren Wigornienſis.</hi>—And when he and his <hi>Normans</hi> put the State into a Convulſion, by their Oppreſſions, ſeveral of the <hi>Saxon</hi> chief Nobility took Arms to defend their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Laws, as having learned of their Anceſtors, <hi>aut Liberta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, aut Mortem,</hi> Liberty or Death. <hi>Argumentum Antinor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manicum,</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:94791:35"/>p. 26.<note n="*" place="margin">There is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notable Compact related to be made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Stigand</hi> A. B. of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, Egel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine</hi> Abbot of St. <hi>Auſtins Canterb.</hi> and the Kentiſh men, who armed themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>William:</hi> and being ready to engage, a Parley is deſired. The Ambaſſadors of the Kentiſh-men were commanded to tell <hi>William</hi> to this purpoſe. Moſt Renowned Duke, The Men of <hi>Kent</hi> do meet thee, they will be thy Friends, and will obey thy Power; if thou grant their juſt Demands, as thoſe that contend to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Liberty received from their Anceſtors, and their Country Laws and Cuſtoms, and that will not be brought under Servitude, which they have not tried, and been uſed to, nor bear new Laws. They can bear Royal Power, but cannot bear Domination. Receive the Kentiſh-men with undiminiſhed and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched Liberty, reſerved Manners and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſages, their Ancient Laws; receive them not as Servants, but Subjects, well affected to thee. But if thou ſtrive to take away their Liberty, and Immunity of their Laws, thou ſhalt take away their Lives at once; for they chuſe rather to fight at the hazard of Battel with thee, and to fall in the Field under the power of certain Enemies, than in the Court under uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Laws. For although the other Engliſh can ſuffer Servitude, yet Liberty is the Property of the Men of <hi>Kent.</hi> The King diſturbed with this Speech, and other Difficulties, took Counſel, for many Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>non neceſſitate magis, quàm voluntate,</hi> he granted that they ſhould live after their Ancient Laws. <hi>Itaque inter Gulielmum &amp; Cantios, initum foedus fuit, &amp; obſides utrinque dat. Antiquitas Britannicae,</hi> p. <hi>108.</hi> Here's an Original Contract with the Arch-biſhop and Abbot, and Kingdom of <hi>Kent.</hi> If you ſay, It was lawful for them to reſiſt an Invader, and a Conqueror: Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he claimed to the Kingdom by an Hereditary Right, as Kinſman, and Heir by Gift to <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor; as right Heir to the Crown, by Succeſſion, as his Succeſſors and Sons, alſo all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dg, who were choſen to the Crown, out of the order of natural deſcent.—See ſeveral Charters quoted to prove this. <hi>Argumentum Antinormanicum,</hi> p. <hi>19, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> And whereas it were to be wiſh'd, that there had been a continual intire Confidence preſerved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Kings and their Subjects, and that there had never been any Forfeiture made, or Queſtion about it: yet there are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures too often made; and though a People ſhould not be haſty to take the Advantage of the King's Weakneſs, yet there's a time when they ought to ſhew, that there is, and muſt be, a Power in a Common-wealth to ſave it ſelf from Ruin. And they cannot anſwer it to God, themſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, nor Poſterity, if they ſhall ſuffer a King, deſpirited and diſabled by God, to recover Strength, when they ſaw how it had been imploy'd, if Divine Providence had not diſarm'd Him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Gentleman goes on to teach us, that a Parliament and a Convention are two different things; the latter for want of the King's Writs, and Concurrence, having no ſhare in the Legiſlative Power. This is as much as to ſay, What have the Convention to do with the Affairs that lay before them? Well, let it be granted, that there is a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Convention and the Parliament: I do humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, with reverence to thoſe Awful Aſſemblies, That the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:94791:36"/>Convention being called in an Extraordinary Caſe, for an Extraordinary Work, were truſted with an Extraordinary Great Power by the Community of <hi>England.</hi> The Real Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty is in the Community of <hi>England.</hi> The Form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was diſſolved. It is true the Community was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the Original, and pure ſtate of Liberty, to frame a new Structure, new from the Foundation, becauſe there were Heirs in pretence, in view, and in expectation: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were obliged in Conſcience to do right to them that had the moſt undoubted Right. But the Settlement of the Government, in the Perſon, or Perſons, was in them. They were the Higheſt Power to determine the Pretence of the Nominal Prince of <hi>Wales:</hi> The Order, Limitation, and Settlement of the Succeſſion was in them. And though they had not the Formality of a Parliament, becauſe of the Defect of a King, they wanted not an Original Power to give under God, and for God, Life and Form to the Government it ſelf. The Legiſlative Power is the King, the Houſe of Lords, and Houſe of Commons. The Buſineſs of the Convention was not to make particular Laws, and they did not exerciſe a Legiſlative Power, but they were put upon it how to re-eſtabliſh the Government, as near as poſſibly they could, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Ancient Conſtitution. And in that reſpect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to conſtitute and declare the Perſons, who were to have a part in the regular enacting of Laws, they had not a leſs, but a greater Power than is ordinarily exerted in Parliament. They were not adviſing how to draw up a new Form or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; there were Ancient Land-marks to bound them, and the Model of the Building was in their Eye; and there were Ancient Laws and Cuſtoms, both Common and Statute, in Force; but there wanted an Adminiſtrator, a Soveraign to look to the Adminiſtration and executive Part. And the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Methods were broken by another who was obliged to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them. They had as exact a reſpect to the Ancient Methods as poſſibly could be had, in obſerving the number of Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives, and giving notice to the Electors to chuſe their Repreſentatives and Truſtees. And they had the Authority of Laws, and Neceſſity both, for what they did. The Laws, by virtue of which they acted, were Cuſtoms immemorial, to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:94791:36"/>meet and conſult about the Publick Good, the Good of the Whole being the great End of Society, and Government. The Law of Nature was ſufficient to call them together: And the urgent Law of Neceſſity laid upon them this Duty, which was not of their own making, as is viſible to all clear-ſighted Men.</p>
               <p>As great things have been done in the Days of our Fathers, out of the ordinary Rules, that were never thought to be ill done. Inſtance is given, not in <hi>Hen.</hi> the 7th, but in the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and Proclamation of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt. One Anſwer to this Demand may be, <q>That Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s wiſe Council did foreſee, that this was an effectual, if not the only way to prevent greater Miſchiefs and Effuſion of Blood, which in all probability had followed, if this Courſe had not been taken. And in an Extraordinary Caſe, ſome Extraordinary Thing, tending to the Publick Good, may lawfully be done. <bibl>
                        <hi>Lawſon. Pol. S. &amp; Civil.</hi> p. 87.—</bibl>
                  </q>
Our Convention will merit an honourable Memorial of all Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, for what they have done in our extraordinary Danger and Confuſion. We are in a way to Happineſs, if Unthankfulneſs and Murmuring doth not caſt us back. And ſuch Papers as theſe will not at all help us towards Peace and Quietneſs. I have no mind to deal any further with him; I am ſorry for him, that he hath given ſuch juſt Provocation to Authority, as he hath by many Paſſages in it.</p>
               <p>Sir, I thank you for any thing you communicate to me: Now let me put into your Hand, a Rational, Moderate, and Convincing Paper. <hi>The lawfulneſs of taking the New Oaths aſſerted.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhould be glad to be ſatisfied in the Point of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> My Conſcience is not at eaſe, and I am afraid I ſhall offend one way or other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>I am glad Our King, Queen, and Parliament, are ſo moderate and patient with Our new Diſſenters and Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. There are two ſorts we would wiſh at eaſe in their own Minds, and for their own Sakes,<note place="margin">Allegiance not due to the late King.</note> and of many that are jealous of ſome ſtrange Mutations among us. But can we expect ſo great a Deliverance, without any ſigns of Danger? Man is a ſullen moroſe Creature, if he be not pleaſed. But
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:94791:37"/>now God, with a holy Reverence be it acknowledged, is <hi>pleaſing Himſelf,</hi> whether you be pleaſed or not. How long ſhall it be before he have your good-will to advance his own Glory? He hath patiently been gratifying you many Years; even to the giving you the King you preferr'd before all things. You have tried him, grew afraid of him, talk'd boldly of him, and acted too to diſpleaſe him, and towards his removal alſo. And now, what's the matter? what would you have? Can you neither be well with him, nor well without him? How many of you acted, as if you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd him to be no King? that the Obligation was diſſolved between you and Him? This ingenuous moderate Gentleman, preſſeth that handſomely and home enough. May I be ſo bold to ſay ſomething upon this tender Argument of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? What though many of you knew what Deſigns were laid, and conceal'd them from the King? did neither argue againſt them, nor eſtrange your ſelves from the Conſpirators, preach'd not one piece of a Sermon againſt them, but went with them, or ſent to them, aſſiſted, countenanced, well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com'd them Home, ſubſcribed the Aſſociation, voted for Members of the Convention, or joined, being choſen? And yet now recoile! All this and Conſcience ſtand in a Man's way, and put him not only to a ſtand, but make him retreat in diſorder and fear! And tenderneſs of Conſcience is to be kindly uſed: and for Oaths, in particular, in an Age wherein they have been common to a Sin, and ſlighted to a high pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of the Holy God. I cannot ſtay long upon this. But in ſhort,</p>
               <p n="1">1. I grant that Allegiance is due to the Perſon of a King; and not only to his Crown and Dignity: but then, that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that poſſeſſeth that Crown and Dignity, is not conſidered abſolutely in his Natural Capacity, but in his Political, as veſted with the Crown and Dignities of a King.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Perſon of a King, as King, in the lawful poſſeſſion of the Crown, is intruſted with the Adminiſtration of the Government, according to the Laws of the Kingdom, which he is bound to God, and the Kingdom, by Promiſe and Oath, to obſerve. And he ought to give himſelf to the actual exerciſe of that Truſt and Authority which he hath</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:94791:37"/>
               <p n="3">3. The Soveraign of <hi>England,</hi> is only Soveraign for Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, according to the Laws made by the joint Powen of the two Houſes of Parliament with him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The natural Perſon to whom we are Subjects, and are obliged to be true and faithful to, as true Subjects, (How can he watch for our Good; if he be not ſecure from Danger from us, and of our Subjection and Obedience as ready to ſerve him, who is the Miniſter of God for good to us?) The Perſon, I ſay, to whom we owe Allegiance, is that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon endowed with Authority and Majeſty for the Ends of his Office.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If He aſſume a greater Power than he hath by the Laws and Conſtitution, or endeavour by Arts and Force to change the Government into another form, or deprive the Subjects of their Fundamental Rights; then though he be the ſame Natural Perſon to whom we promiſed Allegiance, he is not the ſame Moral or Political Perſon. He is not that King to whom we are Subjects, but another, quite contrary to that Majeſty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by us.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Allegiance is during the Life of the King, if while he lives he continueth to be King. He may forfeit to God: And if God diſable him, or remove him, Subjects are diſcharged for their Allegiance, while God hath depoſed him. He may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit to his People, if the Kingdom be <hi>Regnum pactionatum, &amp; non abſolutum.</hi> Great Failures come ſhort of Forfeitures. And if a King not only ceaſe to rule and defend according to his place, but be ſo far perverted as to ſet up his Will, and ſtrive to carry all before it, againſt the Religion and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of his People, they ſhould be ſlow to Wrath and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, or to recover their own Rights by Wars, and not at all by Injuſtice. Many Miſeries are rather to be endured than the Miſeries of War.</p>
               <p n="7">7. It conduceth much to ſatisfy Conſcience, (to underſtand what Allegiance is. <hi>Ligantia, &amp; inde ligiantia, &amp; Allegiantia</hi>) <hi>vinculum arctius inter ſubditum &amp; Regem, invicem connectens.</hi> The Bond, Covenant, or Compact, by which a King and his Subjects are mutually bound to one another, <hi>Hunc ad Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectionem, &amp; juſtum Regimen: illos ad Tributa &amp; debitam ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectionem.</hi> The King is bound to Protection, and juſt Rule
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:94791:38"/>and Government: the People to pay Tribute and due Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. The learned <hi>Spellman,</hi> Gloſſ. Dr. <hi>Robert Auſtin,</hi> who hath taken pains to ſtate it, according to the Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Judges in <hi>Calvin's</hi> Caſe, gives this deſcription of Allegiance. <q>Ligeance is a Quality of Soul, whereby were are diſpoſed to bear all Truth and Faith to the Perſon of the King, his Crown and Dignity, ready to yield him all true Obedience, according to the Laws of Nature, of God, and the Realm wherein we live. <bibl>
                        <hi>Tract of Allegiance not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach'd by the Parliaments taking Arms.</hi> c. 2.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Let us revive the Oaths wherein the promiſe of Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity is made, and thence alſo gather ſomething for our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in this Caſe. And here, I will begin.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Caſe is hardeſt upon them, who took the Oaths ſince the late King did manifeſtly act contrary to the Duty of his Place. But yet, the words of the Oath, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly made to him, <hi>believing him</hi> to be the Lawful and Rightful King of this Realm. Now he is Lawful King, who hath a Lawful Right, and is no Pretender or Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; or he is Lawful King, who is no Tyrant in Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, nor Uſurper of Power above or contrary to Law. How any Man could underſtandingly ſwear, his belief of his being Lawful King, without ſuch a diſtinction, I cannot conceive. And then it is to be conſidered, that he is the lawful King who governs according to Law, or at leaſt not contrary to Law in the main; and then he being the King recognized by the Subject, who ſwears Allegiance to him, if he prove quite contrary, How can he, who own'd him under a true Notion of him, be bound to him, when he is corrupted from what he was taken to be? He took him for his King, who is King by Law, and doth not bend himſelf to overthrow it; but when he ceaſeth to govern his Subjects as Subjects, he diſclaims the governing them as Subjects, and his own being their King, ſaith Dr. <hi>Falkner. Chr. Loyalty, l.</hi> 2. c. 5. p. 544, &amp;c. The Relation of an Engliſh Subject, is to an Engliſh, not an Abſolute King. If one term of the Relation be chang'd or ceaſed, the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the other Relate, and Correlate, ceaſeth. <hi>Ceſſante
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:94791:38"/>perſonâ relata naturali ceſſat obligatio perſonalis. Ceſſante rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione vel perſonâ Civili, ceſſat obligatio talis, quâ talis.</hi> The natural Father dying, the relation to him is at an end, and the Obligation to Duty is diſſolved. The moral and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Relation, and political Perſon ceaſing to be what he ought to be, the Relation and Obligation dies. A King is not bound to govern or protect Traitors. Nor are Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects bound to Allegiance and Obedience to him that is not their King. See the <hi>Chriſtian Directory; Caſes, Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Vows, and Promiſes,</hi> p. 703. And Mr. <hi>Lawſon</hi> is ſhort and poſitive; <q>The perſonal Majeſty of a King with us, requires ſubjection whilſt he lives, and governeth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law; but upon his Death, or Tyranny in Exerciſe, or acting to the Diſſolution of the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Conſtitution, he ceaſeth to be a Soveraign, and the obligation as to Him ceaſeth, <hi>p.</hi> 214. <hi>Polit. Sacra &amp; Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilis.</hi> In a word, ſo many ways as Majeſty and Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may be loſt, ſo many ways this Obligation may be loſt. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. All that concerns the Papal pretended Powers (of doing Evil) in the Oath, remains true for ever. The only Clauſe in the Oath, in which any can think himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, is the Promiſe; <q>I will bear faith and true Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to his Majeſty his Heirs and Succeſſors, and Him and them will defend to the uttermoſt of my Power againſt all Conſpiracies and attempts whatſoever.</q>
The reſolution of this Doubt depends upon the former. Plots and treacherous Conſpiracies, are practices unworthy of Chriſtians againſt the worſt of Tyrants. The ways of defence muſt be lawful. But who was that King which you promiſed to defend, and to bear Faith to? Was it not to your Lawful King, in the lawful Exerciſe of his Authority? If you were a Servant to his Arbitrary Will, if you had defended him, and ſerved him to perſecute the true Religion, or to remove and corrupt it, or to ſet up Arbitrary Power, you were a Traitor againſt God and your Country. Your Oath was a Bond of Iniquity, and ought now to be repented of: Had you fought for him when he was gone to the Camp to fight againſt the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:94791:39"/>Kingdom, you had been a Traitor to <hi>England</hi> for whoſe good only Kings are ordained.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If you are enſnared with the Opinion of the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales</hi>'s being the next Heir, you are to be pitied if you are ſincere in your Opinion. The great Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the higheſt Judges in the Kingdom, ſaw the Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in favour of his Royal Birth, and Natural Deſcent; and what ſwaying Preſumptions and Reaſons are produced and publiſh'd againſt him; and have rejected him, and judged him no lawful Heir. And if you had much more to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm your Opinion of his Birth, you ought to acquieſce in their Higheſt Judgment and Determination. And if you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve never ſo honourably of the late King, that he would not impoſe upon us, yet he might be impoſed upon. But when we conſider how Popiſh Principles corrupt Nature, you have no reaſon to be confident. And if you are not foreſtall'd and partial, you have much more reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that our Gracious King and Queen, who expreſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs in all that they ſpeak or do, that they would abhor to deprive a Right Heir of the Priviledg of his Birth, to gain a Kingdom too ſoon; when they were no further diſtant from it, and ſtood in ſo little need of it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But then, if you inſiſt upon it, Why did not the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Heir ſucceed in Order? This is one of our marve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Bleſſings; and we have cauſe to acknowledg the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Goodneſs of our Queen, that ſhe conſented to, and approved of the Method and Order of the Settlement of the Crown, by a wiſe Act of the Convention, to cut off Debates, and to ſhorten the way to a happy Settlement. If her Majeſty be well pleaſed, and her Royal Highneſs in a better ſtate than ſhe was in before, what Cauſe have you to be diſſatisfied? There is no ſuch exactneſs and nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be found in moſt of our Succeſſions in the Throne. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> was a very wiſe and learned good Man, and his words are worth our following; <hi>Nihil anxiè diſputan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt, quo jure, quarè injuriâ Principes adepti ſunt ſuam po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatem. Illud potiùs agendum eſt, ut Magiſtratus praeſentes revereamur;</hi> in <hi>Rom. c.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 1. Let us not anxiouſly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute Princes Titles; let us rather mind this, that we ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:94791:39"/>and fear the preſent Magiſtrates. I do not ſpeak this, as if I doubted the lawfulneſs of the preſent happy, happy Settlement; but for your ſake. King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt ſpake it; <q>I am ſince come to that Knowledg, that an Act of Parliament can do greater Wonders, than unite <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Great Britain.</hi>
                  </q>
And that old wiſe Man, Treaſurer <hi>Burleigh,</hi> was wont to ſay, <q>He knew not what an Act of Parliament can do in <hi>England;</hi> 
                     <bibl>Speech in <hi>Star-Chamber.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
And ſome great Lawyers, in a Parliament of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Mr. <hi>Yelver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> afterwards Speaker and Judg, ſaid, <q>That to ſay the Parliament had no Power to determine of the Crown, was High Treaſon.</q>
And Mr. <hi>Mounſon</hi> ſaid, <q>It were horrible to ſay, that the Parliament had no Authority to determine of the Crown; <bibl>Sir <hi>S. Dew</hi>'s Journal, <hi>p.</hi> 164, 176.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And what cannot a Convention, a Repreſentative of the Community do? and what Parliament will not confirm what they have done? And what good Man will be ſo cloudy and ſullen, as not to rejoice for what is done, to the unſpeakable Comfort of Proteſtant Countries, and of our own Times, and Poſterity after us, if we ſin not away our Mercies.</p>
               <p>Theſe Things thus conſidered; I pray give me leave to come up cloſe to you.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Do you think in your Conſcience, that <hi>James</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond did govern the Nation according to Law? Did he chuſe the moſt of his Judges to do impartial Juſtice? Did he really deſign a pack'd Parliament for the good of the Proteſtant, the Proteſtant Religion, the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and our Brethren abroad? Was his daily augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Army, for our Protection, and Defence, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not? Did many Noble Officers, and others of his Army, believe it? Why did not they defend and aſſiſt him then? And do you hold your ſelf bound in Allegiance to ſuch a King? Shew me ſuch a King conſtituted by our Laws: ſhew me Law for ſuch Allegiance. See the words of Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> above; What Legiance binds the King to, and upon what condition we promiſe Allegiance.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:94791:40"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But if he break with me, I will keep Oath to him, and be his Liege Subject.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>You will! If he then at this time ſhould ſend an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to you to come to him, and ſerve him in your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in your Purſe, in your Capacity, with your Counſel; and that againſt your own Native Country, would you go? Would you ſerve him in his Wars againſt us? If not, what ſignifies your Allegiance? If you aſſiſt, are you not a Traitor to God and your Countrey, to whom your Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance is due, before it is due to the King. Remember your Duty to ſerve the King, is in God, and for God, and not for Popery againſt God; ſo the Prayer in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But I will not oppoſe his Return, if he ſhould attempt it, to recover his own Lawful Inheritance, and to rule his People.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>If ever he ſhould attempt to return, you think it will be by Force, don'd ye? And do you think it will be, to be a Nurſing-Father to the Church, and a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Governour over the People? or will it not rather be to Revenge, and Conquer, and with more Curſes from the Pope, and Fire in his Boſom againſt Proteſtants, and Fury for Popery? And you will not as much as pray againſt him, nor be delivered from him, nor help to preſerve our Religion and Country from Popiſh Tyranny? without which you cannot rationally look for him, if the way were never ſo open and eaſy.—</p>
               <p>Will you be ever able to prove a Popiſh King to be a Lawful King of <hi>England?</hi> when you do, then you will have an anſwer to this Argument. That King who accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Principles of his Religion, and conſequently the perſwaſion of his Conſcience, muſt endeavour to promote his Own, and to root out our Religion, and with it our Laws by which it is eſtabliſhed, is a King inconſiſtent with his Government, and drives contrary to the End of it, and by conſequence is no King for ſuch a Kingdom. But a Popiſh, (eſpecially a Jeſuited King, as they boaſt him to be) is ſuch a King: therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And will you aſſiſt and ſerve ſuch a King, as bound in Conſcience? then your
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:94791:40"/>Oath is, <hi>vinculum iniquitatis;</hi> and by it you cannot aſſiſt him, but you muſt do Iniquity, or neglect a Duty, and violate the Bonds of all other Relations. Can the performance of your Oath to <hi>James</hi> the late King, conſiſt with the publick Safety and Welfare of the Church and Kingdom? Then, <hi>non eſt ſervandum juramentum, cujus Executio, cum ſalute publicâ, cum honeſtate &amp; bonis moribus pugnaret:</hi> You a Doctor, I will not Engliſh it, I have neither Time, nor Paper to ſpare. It is a Rule about Oaths, among others, laid down by the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Rivet; Explic. Decal Juramenti obligatio qualis.</hi> Can your late King give you Protection, and the Benefit of Laws? If not, can you think your ſelf bound in Conſcience to be his Subject, and owe him Allegiance? Kings are the Shields of the Earth, to give Protection. Therefore they are choſen of Men, and given of God. That's the Conſideration that moves you to ſubjection: if that cannot be had from Him, are you not free? That's the Lige, the Ligeance between the King and Subject; if he cannot, and that by his Fault, the Bond is diſſolved: Who broke firſt? he with the Kingdom, or his Subjects with him? <hi>Si una partium prior juramentum violaverit in re mutuò promiſſa, altera ſolvitur obligatione; Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet.</hi> L. cit.—R. 4.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <p>But he was Diſabled, he was forced by his Subjects. And therefore it is not his fault that he cannot govern or protect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.</speaker>
               <p>He was deſpirited by him who cutteth off the Spirit of Princes, and diſabled, to a Wonder of Divine Power over him. Did he grant what his Subjects deſired, according to their Right and Duty? or hath he ever ſince his going, made an offer to return to <hi>govern by Law?</hi> You know his Mind, and his Engagements; blind not your ſelf. Was the leaſt Violence offered, or threatned, if he would ſtay, and not begon?—I know who ſaid it, but doth he not wrong our King and Nobles? To eaſe you by a Concluſion, Doctor, hath God wrought any Deliverance for us? If not, where are your Senſes? if he hath; why will you not help us to thank God our Saviour? And why will you not own Our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental Saviour? you will pray him in Grumbling, and Withdrawing, and Diſobedience, and omiſſion of Duty! Is
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:94791:41"/>that the way on't? — I muſt beg pardon for this Liberty, and do remember, that if God and Man ſet a King and Queen to bear Rule, I believe our King and Queen to be by Divine Deſignation, and Humane Lawful Ordination. I owe, and hope to pay true Allegiance to them, and therefore I owe none to any other King. If our King and Queen give you the Benefit of their Protection, the Benefit and Comfort of the true Religion, and the Peace of your Country, as you may have, while they have it, you will be obliged in Conſcience to pay Allegiance to them; and you cannot pay Allegiance to two contrary Supremes; if you owe to Our King and Queen, you owe it not to Him that was once your King. Sir, I have no pique at any particular Perſon, to expoſe or diſpleaſe, my Deſign is Charity, and to ſerve the Common-Good. And if I have done any acceptable Service to God, and any Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, I ſhall be glad. <hi>Glory to God on High, on Earth Peace, and good Will towards and among Men.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. line 5. read <hi>afraid.</hi> P. 6. in <hi>T. 2d,</hi> the Scripture doth conſtitute <hi>no</hi> perpetual Form, inſert <hi>no.</hi> P. 13. l. 3. dele <hi>whom,</hi> and read, who is wonderful in working. P. 14. <hi>T.</hi> 2. dele <hi>non,</hi> and read <hi>legibus ſolutus.</hi> P. 23. Margin, r. Dr. <hi>Fern.</hi> P. 25. dele <hi>Hobs</hi> in the Margin, and after <hi>Pol. Sacr. &amp; Civil,</hi> add <hi>c.</hi> 15. <hi>p.</hi> 125. And Anſw. to <hi>Hobs, p.</hi> 17. begin the next Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. The Learned Author of the Rights of the Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is a different Sentence.</p>
            <p>The reſt of the Sheets the Author did not ſee, therefore the Reader is entreated to correct or pardon the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's Faults therein.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:94791:41"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed and Sold by <hi>Jonathan</hi> Robinſon, at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, relating to the great Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Affairs in <hi>England, 1688, 1689.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>☞ AN Account of the Reaſons of the Nobility and Gentry's Invitation of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> into <hi>England;</hi> Being a <hi>Memorial</hi> from the Engliſh Proteſtants concerning their Grievances; with a large Account of the Birth of the Prince of <hi>Wales:</hi> preſented to their Highneſſes the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Political and Hiſtorical Papers relating to the Preſent Juncture of Affairs in <hi>England,</hi> in Ten Parts; which will be Continued from Time to Time, according as Matter occurs.</p>
            <p>A Brief Hiſtory of the Succeſſion of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected out of the Records, and the moſt Authentick Hiſtorians; written for the Satisfaction of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Wonderful Predections of <hi>Noſtredamus, Grebner, David Pareus,</hi> and <hi>Antonius Torquatus;</hi> wherein the Grandeur of their Preſent Majeſties, the Happineſs of <hi>England,</hi> and Downfall of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> are plainly Delineated. With a large Preface, ſhewing, That the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> has not been obſcurely foretold to their Majeſties <hi>William</hi> the <hi>3d,</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> late Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> and that the People of this Ancient Monarchy have duly contributed thereunto, in the preſent Aſſembly of Lords and <hi>Commons,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Objections of Men of different Extremes.</p>
            <p>A Seaſonable Diſcourſe, wherein is examined, what is lawful during the Confuſions and Revolutions of Government, eſpecially in the Caſe of a King deſerting his Kingdoms; and how far a Man may lawfully conform to the Powers and Commands of thoſe, who with Various Succeſſes hold King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. Whether it be lawful.
<list>
                  <item>(1) In Paying Taxes.</item>
                  <item>(2) In perſonal Service.</item>
                  <item>(3) In taking of Oaths.</item>
                  <item>(4) In giving up himſelf to a final Allegiance.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>A Seaſonable Treatiſe; wherein is proved, That King <hi>William</hi> (commonly called the <hi>Conqueror</hi>) did not get the <hi>Imperial Crown</hi> of <hi>England</hi> by the Sword, but by the Election and Conſent of the People. To whom he ſwore to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the <hi>Original Contract</hi> between King and People.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to a Paper Intituled, <hi>The Deſertion Diſcuſſed:</hi> being a Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Proceedings of the late Honourable Convention, in their Filling up the Throne with King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:94791:42"/>
            <p>An Exact Collection of the Debates of the Houſe of Commons (particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly ſuch as relate to the Bill of Excluſion, a Popiſh Succeſſor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) held at <hi>Weſtminſter, Octob.</hi> 21. 1680; Prorogued the 10th, and Diſſolved the 18th of <hi>January</hi> following. With the Debates of the Houſe of Commons at <hi>Oxford,</hi> Aſſembled <hi>March.</hi> 21. 1680. Alſo a Juſt and Modeſt Vindication of the Proceedings of the ſaid Parliaments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Julian's</hi> Arts to Undermine and Extirpate Chriſtianity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Samuel Johnſon.</hi> The Impreſſion of which Book was made in the Year 1683, and has ever ſince lain buried under the Ruins of all thoſe Engliſh Rights which it endeavoured to defend; but by the Auſpicious and Happy Arrival of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> both They and It have obtained a Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Gilbert Burnet</hi> (now Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) his Tracts, in Two Vollumes; in which are contained ſeveral Things relating to the Affairs of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Myſtery of Iniquity, working in the Dividing of Proteſtants, in order to the ſubverting of Religion, and our Laws, for al moſt the ſpace of thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years laſt paſt, plainly laid open. With ſome Advices to Proteſtants of all Perſwaſions, in the preſent Juncture of our Affairs. To which is added, A Specimen of a Bill for uniting of Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>Liberty of Conſcience now highly neceſſary for <hi>England,</hi> humbly repreſented to this preſent Parliament.</p>
            <p>An Enquiry into, and Detection of the Barbarous Murther of the late Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> (now under conſideration of a Committee of the Houſe of Lords): Or, a Vindication of that Noble Perſon, from the Guilt and Infamy of having deſtroyed himſelf.</p>
            <p>An Account of the Trial of Mr. <hi>Papillon.</hi> To which is added, The Matter of Fact in the chuſing of Sheriffs in Sir <hi>John Moor</hi>'s Year, now under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Committee for Grievances.</p>
            <p>A Collection of ſtrange Predictions of Mr. <hi>J. P.</hi> for the Years 1687, and 1688; about K. <hi>James</hi> the Second, Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and the ſcampering away of many great Miniſters of State.</p>
            <p>Arguments againſt the Diſpenſing Power, in Anſwer to L. C. J. <hi>Herbert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Royal Cards;</hi> Being a lively Repreſentation of the late Popiſh and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical Deſigns, and of the wonderful Deliverance of this Kingdom from the ſame, by the glorious Expedition of <hi>William Henry</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> now King of <hi>England,</hi> (whom God long preſerve) in curious Copper Plates. Price <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> a Pack.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
